<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An account of a voyage from Archangel in Russia, in the year 1697 of the ship and company wintering near the North Cape in the latitude of 71, their manner of living, and what they suffered by the extream cold : also, remarkable observations of the climate, country and inhabitants : together with a chart, describing the place where they lay, land in view, soundings, &amp;c. / by Tho. Allison, commander of the ship ; published at the request of the Russia Company, chiefly for the benefit of those who sail that way ...</title>
            <author>Allison, Thomas, fl. 1697.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 138 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 68 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A23821</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A1217</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14608</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11921222</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11921222</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50975</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A23821)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50975)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 47:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An account of a voyage from Archangel in Russia, in the year 1697 of the ship and company wintering near the North Cape in the latitude of 71, their manner of living, and what they suffered by the extream cold : also, remarkable observations of the climate, country and inhabitants : together with a chart, describing the place where they lay, land in view, soundings, &amp;c. / by Tho. Allison, commander of the ship ; published at the request of the Russia Company, chiefly for the benefit of those who sail that way ...</title>
                  <author>Allison, Thomas, fl. 1697.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[18], 96 [i.e. 112] p. : maps.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for D. Brown ... and R. Parker ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. [16].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Soviet Union --  Description and travel --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50975:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50975:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ACCOUNT OF A VOYAGE FROM <hi>ARCHANGEL</hi> IN RUSSIA, In the Year 1697. Of the Ship and Company Wintering near the North Cape in the Latitude of 71. Their Manner of Living, and what they Suffered by the Extream Cold. ALSO Remarkable Obſervations of the Climate, Country and Inhabitants. Together with A Chart, deſcribing the place where they lay, Land in View, Soundings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Tho. Alliſon,</hi> Commander of the Ship.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed at the Requeſt of the <hi>Ruſſia</hi> Company; chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the benefit of thoſe who ſail that way, as well as for the ſatisfaction of the Curious, or any who are concerned in that Trade.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>D. Brown</hi> at the <hi>Black Swan and Bible</hi> without <hi>Temple-bar,</hi> and <hi>R. Parker</hi> at the <hi>Unicorn</hi> under the <hi>Royal Exchange.</hi> 1699</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:50975:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50975:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable Sir <hi>Benjamin Ayloffe,</hi> GOVERNOUR, And to the Worſhipful the Conſuls and Aſſiſtants of the <hi>Ruſſia</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured and Worthy Sirs,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOu muſt not expect an Excuſe for my Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when the Work was in Obedience to Your Command: and if I have fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the perfection of it, I hope my Good Intentions will be accepted, and my inability but lightly Taxed.
<pb facs="tcp:50975:3"/> I proteſt ſolemnly I never had any fond deſire of appearing in print; but my main Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is to do you Faithful Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; and I reckon this a part of it. And beſides, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of your Buſineſs, and diſcharge of the Truſt repoſed in me, I think I ought to do the utmoſt in my Station or Calling, for the general good of Mankind, and the Benefit of Poſterity. It may be ſaid I was unfortunate in this Voyage, but not unſucceſsful, in preſerving the Cargo and returning with the Ship. And in reading it, I hope you will find, no wilful neglect, or
<pb facs="tcp:50975:3"/> want of skill was the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of what happend; ſince others at that time ſuffer'd the ſame with me, and ſome worſe. And if by that means I have had opportunity of informing my ſelf better of the Coaſt, and thereby of Inſtructing others, I ſhall not torment my ſelf or repine at what I have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered. We ought to acquieſce in every thing as by Divine Providence ordered; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that principle you ſeem to have acted, by your ready allowance of the da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage I charged: which Kind and Honourable Dealing with me I muſt acknowledge to the
<pb facs="tcp:50975:4"/> world, and for ever record in my mind.</p>
            <p>I find it very hard to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear falling into the juſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of your ſeveral Worths; but I know the Bluntneſs of a Seaman, does not ſuit with Haranguing: Beſides, having ſet my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs for ſaying nothing at this time, but what relates to the following Treatiſe; I muſt ſteer thereby, and keep ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. I value your Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and Honour your Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and am in all duty,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt humble Servant,</hi> T. Alliſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:50975:4"/>
            <head>THE BOOKSELLERS TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>FOr your greater ſatisfaction I am inclined, not only to vouch for the Author, and obviate what objections I imagin may be made againſt this brief account; but alſo to give my Opinion frankly, of Writings of this nature, and Voyages in general.</p>
            <p>The Captain I know perſonally to be a man of Ingenuity and Skill in his Profeſſion, and one of great Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racity: that he has been nicely care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful not to mention the leaſt matter poſitively, but what he knows
<pb facs="tcp:50975:5"/> to be truth. The greateſt part of this account, he delivers from his own knowledge; and for what he ſays he was told, he was fully convinced of its reality, before he would make Report of it. 'Tis a moſt abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thing for any one to go abroad, and return with a pretended Journal, of ſurprizing Diſcoveries and ſtrange Occurrences; and make a Linſey-Woolſey ſtory, part Matter of Fact, and part deviſed: or perhaps the whole meer Romance or Fable. Mankind can reap no Improvement from ſuch Relations; and Voyagers are but poor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſiſted from ſuch uncertain Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and ſorry Informations. But ſome, perceiving how fond people are of tales, have put forth Travels patch'd together, and pick'd out of other Books; giving a new date to the Work and a new name to the Compiler; to gull the ignorant, and
<pb facs="tcp:50975:5"/> make a wiſe man mad. Whereas here can be no admittance of fallacy; for we tell you of what was done yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, the perſon and place, and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, if uncertain and falſe, eaſy to be detected.</p>
            <p>And if every one that goes into a Foreign Land, would be punctual to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et down what he meets with there; be careful in obſerving what is rare or uſeful; curious in Draughts of Coaſts or Harbours, and bring home with him ſpecimens or particulars of Plants or Animals, or ought elſe, as the Production or Commodity of the place; our Obſervations, as well Topographical as Natural, might become more full and perfect, and true Learning upon a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter foundation. The mind of man is pleaſed and enlarged, when inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the diverſity of Countries and differences of Climes; and without
<pb facs="tcp:50975:6"/> expoſing himſelf to the hardſhip o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Travel, he may be qualify'd to mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> due compariſon between the Earth under the Line, and nearer the Pole Our bodily wants more readily ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ply'd by the Goods of one Country exchanged for thoſe of another which is as much as to ſay, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce encreaſed and enlivened, and Navigation rendred more eaſy and cheap and leſs dangerous. As to our <hi>Ruſſia</hi> Trade in particular, conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as it is, and ſo adjudged by the laſt Parliament, and the neceſſity of doubling the North Cape, in going and returning, and often at unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable times; what directions are here laid down? and what an uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful diſcovery, for any that ſhall meet with the ſame diſaſter in time to come? I have heard the Captain himſelf ſay, that had he known how the Lands lay; what anchoring places
<pb facs="tcp:50975:6"/> were in the <hi>Fuel,</hi> as well when he got <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut, as when he was forced in, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould have made ſhift to have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ound the way out, dark as the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on was, in a few days after. And he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad reaſon to think as well of his own underſtanding in this part of the world, as any one living, having made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> great many Voyages thither, both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arly and late in the year. 'Tis true, all Maps lately have made the Cape an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſland, but very imperfectly delinea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed the Inlets or Streights; and who knows not, but in time they may be found ſafe to be paſſed, when croſs Winds forbid them going about.</p>
            <p>But in looking further into this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ournal, I gueſs ſome one may not ſo well like, to read ſo often of Winds; ſo much of Froſt and Snow; the diſmal attendants of Winter. He thinks, that to ſay nothing in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, but 'tis a foul day, or very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable
<pb facs="tcp:50975:7"/> weather, is a ſign of grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> want of matter of diſcourſe. All thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is granted to be a fault in time an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> place, when Invention is at liberty and where we have plenty of Subject to talk upon. 'Tis one thing to kee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtrict to a Diary, for the natural Hi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtory of a Country, and anothe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thing with the liberty of a Poet to write a Shepherds Calendar. Ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is no other way of giving any one the Idea of the Temperature of a Climate, than by remarking the weather daily, and the hourly changes of it.</p>
            <p>Others may be mightily chagreen'd at the tedious entertainment of every days letting fall the Anchor, and heaving it up again; of hoiſting and lowering their Yards and Top-Maſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It might be no great diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to thoſe that did it, but it may be ſome to the Reader, if it does but
<pb facs="tcp:50975:7"/> raiſe his pity and compaſſion for 'em, under ſo much labour, and ſuch ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der refreſhment; ſuch uncomforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dark work, with ſuch muzzel'd hands almoſt without Fingers, and Limbs ſo benumm'd and feeble to perform it. Neither was it altogether neceſſary, or meerly impos'd by their Captain as exerciſe; but in order to their ſafety, and to keep themſelves in a poſture, ſuitable to their reviving hopes of getting away It cannot be omitted in relating their ſufferings, and how they ſpent their time, as being part of the ſtory.</p>
            <p>Others again are ſtrangely offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the perpetual mentioning of Dills. Periwinkles, Scallops, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and yet if theſe minute matters had not been ſet down, they would be ready to ſay, how did they go to work to live all the while? they ought to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer themſelves, and to be ſatisfy'd;
<pb facs="tcp:50975:8"/> commend the vigilant Maſter, for providing ſo well for his Houſe, in ordering to each his proportion, and ſo equally directing their ſervices, for the preſervation of the whole Family.</p>
            <p>The ſame anſwer will ſerve for Wooding and Watering; their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of doing and repeating it with ſuch toil and hazard.</p>
            <p>Perhaps a refin'd Linguiſt may be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſted at ſo much Tarpawling expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and ſo many words not allow'd to be <hi>Engliſh.</hi> I ſhall firſt tell him, that this Watry Language, is brought upon Land to be ſhipt off again ſpeedily; for the ſake of ſuch, who underſtand it readily, and have heard it in its proper place. And then I appeal to Gentlemen and Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars: for perſons of Candour and Learning will conſider, that to go about to expreſs this in other terms would make it all Paraphraſe, and
<pb facs="tcp:50975:8"/> that wretched ſtiff and formal. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the words themſelves are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſive enough and diſtinguiſhing, and what a Language need not be aſham'd of They are what are found in other Books of the ſame ſubjects; and if they are not, 'tis pity they ſhould not be received, or made a part of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue, by joyning them with others of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon uſe, and more known. For ſome eaſe to ſuch, an explanation in the Margin has been added to a few, and if they will pleaſe to make en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry into the others, they will have the pleaſure of becoming more knowing than before.</p>
            <p>In a word, our Author has ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly obſerved the order of time, and ſucceſſively mentioned the days, without ſo doing a Journal would be lame and defective. His abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in minute Paſſages, and light
<pb facs="tcp:50975:9"/> Contingencies, was to make the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory full and entertaining. His Maps and Deſcriptions are accura<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e his obſervations as judicious and faithful as any of the ſame kind, and beyond what might be expected: but to give Reaſons, or aſſign Cauſes for ſtrange appearances, change of Wind and Weather, effects of cold, or what elſe betided him, is wholly left to you; and he pretends only to furniſh you with Matter of Fact, upon which you may depend as true</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 21. l. 12. add <hi>in the Height of Summer:</hi> p. 72. l. 19. r. <hi>as w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lay:</hi> p. 74. l. 14. r. <hi>the Wind Southerd:</hi> p. 108. l. 5. for <hi>Maſts</hi> r<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Matts:</hi> p. 109. l. 2. r. <hi>to his:</hi> p. 110. l. 2. r. <hi>and then to the:</hi> Ibid. l. 14. r. <hi>ſhifting between.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:50975:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:50975:10"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="map">
            <pb facs="tcp:50975:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>map of Archangel (?), Russia</figDesc>
                  <p>Calwick on the Cape</p>
                  <p>North Cape Island</p>
                  <p>Flemings Bay</p>
                  <p>Swetwell</p>
                  <p>Old Priest</p>
                  <p>A Scale of 20 degrees to one degree</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:50975:11"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50975:11"/>
            <head>AN ACCOUNT OF A VOYAGE FROM <hi>ARCHANGEL</hi> IN RUSSIA, In the Year 1697.</head>
            <p>I Sailed over the Bar of <hi>Archangel</hi> on the 8th of <hi>October,</hi> 1697. about four in the afternoon, in the Ship called the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n of Yarmouth,</hi> (Burthen 250 Tuns) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d bound for <hi>London;</hi> by that time
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50975:12"/> it grew dark, I came to an Anchor, to g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all things faſt for the Sea: The Win<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> South South Eaſt, cloſe weather.</p>
            <p>The 9th, (being <hi>Saturday</hi>) by the fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> light of the Morning I weighed Ancho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and made the beſt of my way; at 6 in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Evening, I got the length of the Lan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Cats-noſe:</hi> the Wind S. S. E. fine wea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>The 10th, <hi>Sunday.</hi> At break of Day w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were the length of <hi>Croſs</hi> Iſland; and juſt a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it was Dark, I got through the narrow thwart Cape <hi>Loganneſs:</hi> the Wind then a S. S. W. and good weather.</p>
            <p>The 11 <hi>Monday.</hi> As ſoon as it was light I found my ſelf even with the Iſland of <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>baſco;</hi> and at 4 in the afternoon, the High Land of <hi>Swetnoſe</hi> bore South from us, di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtance 15 Miles; from whence I took my departure: The Wind was then at S. Eaſt handſom weather.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tueſday</hi> the 12th proved very fair, and almoſt ſtark Calm; ſo that I made my way W. N. W. but 26 Miles, diſtant from the Place, whence I began my reckoning the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:50975:12"/> day before, to the Noon-Tide of this: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hence forward being computed as part of day enſuing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wedneſday</hi> the 13th, continued ſo Calm <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll the 24 hours, that I made my way North not above 13 miles. The Breezes we had, were at N. W. and W.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thurſday</hi> the 14th, began fair with ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more Wind, firſt at N. N. E. after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward at N. W. with<note n="*" place="bottom">A Squaul, is a ſudden ſhower of Rain, or fall of Snow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>nded with Wind,</note> Squauls. My way was W. by N. diſt. 40 miles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Friday</hi> the 15th, The whole 24 hours the Wind kept ſhifting from N. and W. N. W. and in the night little; my way exceeded not 16 miles, N. W.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saturday</hi> the 16th. For the firſt 12 Hours, the Wind continued to ſhift to and fro, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the W. N. W. and the N. N. E. with uncertain weather. At 8 in the morning it came to the S. W. and began to blow hard; and we had a very great Sea out of the Weſt.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:50975:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Sunday</hi> the 17th. Till Midnight we had fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Squauls, and in the Morning it began to blow from the S.W. ſo as to oblige us to tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in two Reifs of our Topſails; and a grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Sea came rowling out of the Weſt. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding I made my way good N. W. hal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Weſt, diſt. 69 miles. This day I had an obſervation, and found my ſelf in the lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of 70 degrees and 15 minutes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Monday</hi> the 18th. Towards Night i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> proved a ſore Storm, but it came down gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dually, firſt putting us paſt carrying ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Topſails, then our Foreſail; at length, being under a Main Courſe, by four in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, our Main Tack broke. Afterward <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lay under a Mizen during the fret of Wind<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> till it was fair Day, and then I ſet my Mainſail. I made my way that 24 hours N. W. half Weſt 50 miles: the Wind ſhifting from S. Weſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tueſday</hi> the 19th. At 2 in the After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon the Wind came to S. E. by Eaſt, and held Calm all Night: by ſix in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it was Eaſt, ſtill little Wind; but at ten we had ſuch a Gale, that I was forced to hand our Foreſail; and out of the N. W. came the fierceſt of it, freezing hard with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50975:13"/> Howbeit in the twenty four hours, I made my way W. N. W. 25 Miles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wedneſday</hi> the 20th. It continued very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad weather, the Wind at N. W; but at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the Morning the Wind eaſed, and we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et our Foreſail. Then it came to the N. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad to N. E. and ſo to E. I made my way <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. W. by W. 4 miles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thurſday</hi> the 21ſt. By twelve at Noon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Wind was at S. S. E. handſom weather; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t two I found it in the S. S. W. corner, with a Sky ſo fair and clear, that I plainly diſcerned <hi>Terry-berry,</hi> to the S. S. E. 18 miles off. All this 24 hours there came a great Sea out of the Weſt; againſt which I made my way 42 miles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Friday,</hi> the 22d, it continued a hard gale of wind at Weſt, which put us under our Mainſail and Mizen, till two in the morning: Then the wind coming Norther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I tacked and made way N. N. W. 10 miles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saturday,</hi> the 23d, at 8 in the morning I ſaw the <hi>North Kyne,</hi> diſtant 21 miles to the S. by W. and the wind being South, I
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50975:14"/> made the beſt of my way to the Weſt ward.</p>
            <p>At ten it came to W. S. W. and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after to W. N. W. blowing ſo hard as to put me under 3 courſes Reift, ſtanding to the Northward till 12 at night. Then I tacked to the Weſtward, but the wind in 2 hours after came to N. W. by W. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon I tacked to the Northward again, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der three Couſes Reift; but at eight in the morning, I went about to the Weſtward, having made my way this 24 hours W. by N. 27 miles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sunday,</hi> 24. By 12 at Noon the wind was at N. by W. and N. N. W. but by 3 in the Afternoon it came to N. W. by N. with ſo much wind, that I durſt not tack the Ship, for fear of loſing our Main-ſail, and yet I could carry none but that and a Mizen. So I charg'd a good looking out, deeming our ſelves near Land.</p>
            <p>25th, <hi>Monday,</hi> at four in the morning, being Moon-light, we ſaw the Land of the North Cape, two points under our Lee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow. Then we looſed the Fore-Sail, and ſtood to the Eaſtward, under Three Courſes
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50975:14"/> Reift: We likewiſe ſet our Main-Stay-Sail, but ſuch was the ſtreſs of Wind, that it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mmediately flew out of the Bolt-rope. As ſoon as it was day, we plainly perceived we could not weather the Land of <hi>North Kyne.</hi> It continuing very ſquauly.</p>
            <p>After I had well conſider'd our conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I call'd my men together, and told them my Reſolution; which was to run up the Wide<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Fuel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> is an opening between two head Lands, having no bottom in ſight, but a ſeeming Inlet into Land.</note> 
               <hi>Fuel</hi> (that was then before us) while the day laſted: Reaſoning with them, that to ſpend the day in Tacking before it, was to diſable ourſelves, and perhaps ſplit our Sails; and when night came, to drive upon the Rocks, would be to the Hazard of our Lives, Ship, and Goods.</p>
            <p>Thereupon, in hopes of more ſecurity under ſome Point, Iſland, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or in ſome Bay to Anchor, I put the Helm a weather, and ran for the <hi>Fuel;</hi> which, I judged, might be ſeven or eight miles wide.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:50975:15"/>
            <p>Accordingly I hauled up my Fore-Sail, that I might ſee before me while the Squauls of Snow fell; which after they were paſt, I ſet again: Uſing all Diligence that could be, in ſearch of ſome ſhelter from Land, or place of Anchorage.</p>
            <p>At one in the Afternoon I diſcovered an Iſland which had a ſmall Breach off it; but the men in the Tops, and on the Yards, ſaid the opening next the Main was ſo large, that no ſecurity could be under it. Then I ſteered my courſe to the Eaſt ſide of the <hi>Fuel,</hi> (for the Iſland aforeſaid lay on the Weſt) and running up S. E. I ſaw ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing like a Bay; but the Hills ſeemed ſo ſteep, that I was loath to ſhoot my ſelf into it, for fear of having no Anchor Ground. For 'tis generally obſerved by us in ſuch Countries, if the Hills be very high near the Water, there are commonly great depths at little diſtance. So that looking further a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head I eſpyed a ſhore, as I thought, with a handſome deſcent: and concluding ſuch places more likely for my purpoſe, I ſet my Fore-top-ſail and Main-ſail. Then came a ſore Squaul, which forced me to hand my Fore-top-ſail, and haul up my Main-ſail; but before the Squaul was over, I was got
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50975:15"/> paſt that Bay: Yet then I ſaw another point, and our Water ſmoothed much. For that I made way, and ran cloſe to it, ſtill find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no ground with our Lead; but on the other ſide of the point went in a great Bay. With keeping the Lead, I came about the point, and found 25 fathom Water, ſoft Ground: then I let go my Anchor, and got my Skiff out, to carry a Haulfer aſhore; which was no ſooner done, but the Eddy Winds came off the Hills upon the point, and ſwung the Ships Stern ſomewhat too near the ſhore.</p>
            <p>But the Squaul being over, the wind eaſed, and blowing more into the Bay, (which by it its looks promiſed well) I hove up my anchor, and drove further, into the depth of 40 fathom; letting it then drop again. By this time it grew dark; ſo we gave her a whole Cable, and rode in 16 fathom. Then after all things were ſtowed, and we thought our ſelves very well, and went to ſupper, I felt the Ship to rub on the ground. I im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately commanded the Lead to be heaved over the Poop, and found there was not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove two fathom Water. Then I cauſed two Fakes of the Cable to be taken in, and we rode with our Stern in 7 fathom
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50975:16"/> Whereupon I got a ſmall Anchor and Haulſer into my Boat, and rowed into the flat Bay, in 16 fathom; by which means I heaved the Ship further into the depth afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, with very good ground. At the ſame time I ordered the Boat to ſound round the Ship, and found the place where I rubb'd on the ground, to be a point of Rocks lying from the Main on the South ſide, but all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Bay elſe to be good Ground. So we lay all night.</p>
            <p>26th, <hi>Tueſday,</hi> by day light I ſent a Boat with a Mate, to ſee how things were about us; who reported that in the bottom of the Bay run in a good Harbour, and likewiſe that ſome Houſes were in ſight: but upon my re-ſending the Boat, they were found without Inhabitants.</p>
            <p>By that time theſe ſearches had been made, night came on. (Note that we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted ſo much light to make day, as was ſufficient to read by, or wherewith we were able to diſcern a Boat at half a miles di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. For though the Sun might be at that time about three degrees high upon the Meridian, we being under high Land, could not perceive his whole body.) The reſt of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50975:16"/> our men on board were fitting the Ship, by mending the Rigging and Sails. The wind at North Weſt, moderate weather, with ſome Snow. That night I was much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with conſideration of the place where we lay: that if the Wind ſhould come to the North Eaſt with any Gale, we might blow off the Bank, and then into more ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zardous, becauſe more unknown, places.</p>
            <p>27th, <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> at break of day, I got my beſt Bow-anchor aboard, and warped further into the Bay, where I Rid, having withal two Haulſers faſtned to a Rock on ſhore. We continued to fit the Ship for the Sea, when it ſhould pleaſe God to give us opportunity. The wind was yet Northerly, clear weather, ſo that we ſaw Land on the Weſt ſide over againſt us, which we ſaw not the day of our firſt coming in, and I judged it might be eight miles off.</p>
            <p>28th, <hi>Thurſday,</hi> This day proved very bad weather, with much Snow, and the Wind ſhifting ſometime at N. E. at N. and N. W. ſo that we could not but acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the Providence of God, in directing us to move where we were: for had it not been done, we muſt have been blown from
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50975:17"/> our former place. Then I went my ſelf to ſearch, and ſounded the Bay and Harbour all over, and made what diſcovery I cou'd of things about us; finding a good watering place, and plenty of Wood near at hand, At my return, upon complaint of ſome of our mens embezeling and ſtealing our Bread, I ordered it to be locked up. For it began to look with little Hopes of getting out till the light Moon came. We got a Boats load of Wood, and one of Water, that night on Board; and began to conſider further, as to our ſafety in that place, ſhould the Wind Weſter, and break our Haulſer aſhore.</p>
            <p n="29">29, <hi>Friday,</hi> at break of day, I went and ſounded from my Bow-Anchor to the Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ern ſhore, and found 40 Fathom a little from it, ſtill depthning towards the ſaid ſhore. Whereupon arguing with my ſelf, that after removal of the Ship further in, I might ſet ſail, and come out out as eaſily, and yet in the mean time be ſecure in the worſt weather; I removed farther into the Harbour, even to the place where we lay all Winter. This we had ſcarce done, and made our Ship faſt, but it began to blow right in, and ſoon after it proved ſuch a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50975:17"/> ſtorm at N. W. that had we kept our late ſtation, we had in all likelyhood been loſt. Here again our men were made ſenſible of the Goodneſs of God towards us, by a freſh inſtance. Then having account that our Peaſe were unreaſonably waſted, I or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered a Barrel of them, with two great Bags of Bread of two hundred and a half each, to be brought up into the Round<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, with all ſmall proviſions, as Butter and Cheeſe and Fruit, to ſecure them there; and reduced our men to half Allowance, that we might have ſufficient wherewith to go to Sea. For here we abode as Neceſſity drove us, and not with any Intent of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence as yet. I obſerved at this time the days to ſhorten exceedingly, being now not above ſeven hours, according to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained meaning of Day, in the Paragraph aforegoing.</p>
            <p n="30">30th, <hi>Saturday.</hi> I moored the Ship with two Bowers to the Offen, along the Bank; that is to ſay, one to the South Eaſt, and the other to the North Weſt, and carried both the Kedge Anchor and Warp Anchor aſhore, and placed them together, each with one Flook in the dry ſhore, burying them with Stones, for the better holding.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50975:18"/> To one of theſe my Kedge Haulſer, to the other my Stream Cable was faſtened, like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe a new Towline to a great Stone; lying all as one, to the Weſt South Weſt. So between all theſe ſhe ſwung by the Head. Take notice the Harbour was in faſhion like an Oven, lying South Eaſt and North Weſt, being a mile from the Mouth to the bottom and two Cables length, <hi>viz.</hi> 400 yards in Breadth or Wideneſs: and lying thus we ſhut the Ovens mouth; that is, we could not ſo lying, ſee into the wide Fuell. My beſt Bower lay in 21 fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thom, and my ſmall Bower in 19; the middle of the Harbour being of that depth, both upward and downward, but ſhowl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing toward either ſide, with good Clay ground.</p>
            <p>It blew hard all day, with much Snow and ſome ſmall Rain; ſo I ſpread a Sail over my main Deck, the weather being ſo ſharp, there was no ſtanding upon the ſame without it.</p>
            <p n="31">31. <hi>Sunday.</hi> It blew a Storm all day at North Weſt, inſomuch that we could not continue the Covering aforeſaid, but were forced to take it down, and put the Sail together again.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:50975:18"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>diagram of ship in harbor showing water depths (soundings) and shoreline with buildings, trees, and hills</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb facs="tcp:50975:19"/>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:50975:19"/>
            <p>
               <hi>November</hi> 1. <hi>Monday.</hi> I ſent all hands aſhore to get firing; for the Snow encreaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, we feared our Wood would all be bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried under it. Our ordinary manner of Wooding was to go in the Long-boat, with 16 or 18 men to the ſhore upon which the Trees grew, almoſt from the Beach half way up the Hills. They were Birch moſtly, with ſome ſmall Trees like Willows; the biggeſt of either not exceeding a middling mans Thigh: and the appearance of them above the Snow, not above three yards We cut them as the depth of the Snow ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd us, ſome nearer, ſome further from the Root: for the plenty we had eaſed us from digging much. Beſides, unleſs the Snow was newly fallen, the ſurface of it was ſo hard Cruſted by the froſt, as to bear: Notwithſtanding ſome accidentally plunged in now and then, but recoverably. The dragging of the Trees thereby was no leſs eaſie, being upon a deſcent: and we lopped them near the ſhore, for convenient putting on board and ſtowage. We got that day a Long-boat full, that is, about a Cart-load, as I judged, or more,</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:50975:20"/>2d, <hi>Tueſday,</hi> I got two Boats full of Wood more. Much Snow fell this day in Squauls, with hard blaſts from the North Weſt, till towards night.</p>
            <p n="3">3d, <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> It being fair weather, I ſent my Skiff with Hooks and Lines to take Fiſh; but in the <hi>Fuel</hi> they could find no ground with a hundred fathom of Line; yet they made, ſome tryal nearer the ſhore without perceiving any to bite. There were but four men employed in this Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, the reſt went with the Long-boat a Wooding as before, but with greater toil and labour, occaſion'd from light Snow fallen the former night. This night alſo added more, it freezing hard withal, and the Wind Northerly.</p>
            <p n="4">4th, <hi>Thurſday,</hi> it proved fair over head, the Wind North Eaſt and moderate. This day we got a Boats Load of Water, conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of four Hogſheads full: at the ſame time two of our men got up the tops of the Hills to the S.W. ſide, to ſee what they could diſcover; and brought word they had met with the prints of Deers Hoofs, producing a piece of an old Horn they had found, as a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50975:20"/> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony. Likewiſe of Bears, Wolves, and Foxes: theſe three are eaſily diſtinguiſhed; The Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the Bear being flat and long, and like that of a Humane Foot: thoſe of Foxes and Wolves, are like Dogs, the latter big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. They ſaw ſmall creatures too running and playing, which they believed were Foxes. The watering Crew alſo ſaid they ſaw the ſteps of Deer, where they had been.</p>
            <p>The 5th <hi>Friday.</hi> The wind was at South E. but with ſuch a Storm, that we could not think of Looſing our Ship for the Sea. However I ſent 6 men armed aſhore, for diſcovery, or what they could get; but the Wind and Snow was ſo ſevere upon their Faces, that they could not proceed farther than the firſt Hill: ſo they returned and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y reported, they ſaw a River on the Eaſt ſide of the Hill, that was frozen faſt.</p>
            <p>The 6th <hi>Saturday.</hi> I got a Boat load of Wood. It froze extream hard, the wind at N. E. turning to the N. W. towards night, and began to blow.</p>
            <p>The 7th <hi>Sunday.</hi> It proved a freſh of wind at N. W. all day freezing hard.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:50975:21"/>
            <p>The 8th <hi>Monday.</hi> It blew ſo hard at S. W. that it broke all our Shore Faſts, pulle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> home our ſmall Bow Anchor, and dro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Ship on the N. E. ſhore, with her Ste<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> aground; but by good hap our beſt Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Anchor brought her up, and ſwung the Sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> into deep water. So we rode between of Bow Anchor; it proving moderate weath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> towards midnight.</p>
            <p>The 9th, <hi>Tueſday.</hi> I got my Anchor on boar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and moored the Ship in her old place, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> laying the beſt Bower to the N. W. the She Anchor to the S. E. and Small Bower to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> N. E. and carried all Haulſers and Towlin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the Anchors on the dry ſhore, to the V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> S. W. of us. This we did as out of hopes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> getting to Sea this light Moon; for our Rudd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Head was wrung in peices, by a blow g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ven againſt the ground the day before, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſomewhat damaged in the lower part. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> then made the Ship as ſnug as I could, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> taking down our Mizen Top-maſt, Crotche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Yard, and Spritſail Yard, with our Low Yard fore and aft: but our Sails we could not u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bend, being ſo hard frozen. The win<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> came N. W. which forwarded us in faſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning our Ship and that was both our da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and nights work.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:50975:21"/>
            <p>The 10th <hi>Wedneſday.</hi> I got two Haul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers more aſhore, it blowing a hard Gale at S. E. till 10 at night. Then the wind al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ered and became fair. About this time the Hawks we had aboard all died, within few Hours one of another. We had likewiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Foxes to have been brought over, one of which our Men eat ſome days before un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nown to me; and this day they roaſted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nother, which I ſaw, the fleſh looking <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lack like a Hare: but upon taſte, I liked <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſuch rank Veniſon. The third ran <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>own into the Hold and could not be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ently found; but a mouth after having <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>laid the thief with a peice of our Beef, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as knock'd on the head and being too can for food, was thrown over board.</p>
            <p>The 11th <hi>Thurſday.</hi> It Snowed much, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut thawed as it fell; the Wind at N. W. with a ſtrong Gale. I made all haſte poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly to get our Rudder head mended, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xing a piece of Plank on the one ſide of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t. It being bad weather, that was all we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould do in a days ſpace, which exceeded <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot 6 hours, and no better than Twilight. Neither could our men endure the Air at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch Work, longer then a quarter of an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our, without coming in to warm them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lves.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:50975:22"/>
            <p>The 12th <hi>Friday.</hi> I got another piec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Plank on the other ſide of the Rudd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Head, it proving handſom weather and ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> clear; whereby we perceived ſomething i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the lower part of the Rudder as broken but upon tryal with our Poles and Boa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hooks, found only a ſmall piece of the he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bruiſed, with damage inconſiderable.</p>
            <p>The 13th, <hi>Saturday.</hi> It proved fair, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with ſome Snow. I took the Boat an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> rowed into the Bay, on the other ſide of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> point, and at the bottom of it I found River running in, but ſo frozen as to hind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> further diſcovery of it; but by ſoundin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Entrance, we found 12 Foot water <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> half Tide. Going aſhore on the North ſid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I ſaw a great run of water falling into th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Bay thereby, near the ſhore along Woody Valley. Not far from this plac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I obſerved the Snow to lie in Ridge (ſuch as we make upon Land, where we ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our Winter Corn,) its Surface being har<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cruſted with Ice, with ſomething appearing a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bove it like Straw. There were little mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> than the bare ears, without any grain in them four or five Inches long: ſo that thereb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I had hold enough with my hand, to pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> up the whole ſtalk, which was about 3 foo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in length.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:50975:22"/>
            <p>I was under full belief that this was Barley, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at I cou'd not ſatisfie my ſelf, that any had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en reaped off there, ſeeing the Snow co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ered the Stubble. To the unbelieving Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er I have only this to offer, to evince the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſſibility of it, <hi>viz.</hi> That the ſoil was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ood, as appeared by the plenty of Wood <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ear it, the ouzy ſhore, and Clayey bottom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the Bay; the place lying open to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>outh, and defended againſt the North <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſt, by the Mountains. Withal it muſt be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onſidered, that the Sun is here about ſix weeks above the Horizon, and the days be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore and after much longer than with us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <hi>England</hi> at thoſe times. That the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng of this grain to perfection requires not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bove 14 weeks after Seed time, in more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>outhern Regions. At <hi>Narva</hi> in <hi>Livonia,</hi> I my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elf have known the ſame Corn in the Ear, within a month or 5 weeks after it appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed above ground.</p>
            <p>Hereabout I found an Anchoring place, but ſo ſteep that whoever uſes it, muſt truſt chiefly to the faſts he makes on ſhore. There was another alſo at the bottom of the Bay, a mile in; but the haſty depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure of Light made our Diſcovery incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat. So we returned all of us on Board,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:50975:23"/> miſerably cold. I could not but obſerve that as we went and came by the <hi>Fuel</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Wind was at N. W. but where the Ship rode, our men on board had it all day Eaſterly.</p>
            <p>The 14th, <hi>Sunday.</hi> It blew a hard ſtorm a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> N. W. pulling home our beſt Bow-Anchor, until ſuch time as the ſmall Bower and Haulſers aſhore aſſiſted; and then by all three ſhe rode, till the Gale was over, which was not before nine at Night.</p>
            <p>The 15th, <hi>Monday.</hi> The wind was at N. fair; and we hauled our Sheat Anchor farther into the Bay.</p>
            <p>The 16th, <hi>Tueſday.</hi> We had a hard Gale at E. N. E. ſo that it pulled home our Sheat Anchor. There was much Snow all day and night; the wind after ſome time coming to the N. N. E. with ſomewhat more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate weather. At this time two of our Company were mightily for fitting up a Houſe upon Land, and putting proviſion therein for ſubſiſtance, in caſe we ſhould be forced aſhore, and wracked. But I could not comply with ſuch advice; knowing the Ship to be warmer than any thing we could build aſhore, with the Materials,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:50975:23"/> Time and Light we had to do it. Withal I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>agin'd, that if we had had a place to our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſh upon <hi>Terra Firma,</hi> I could not have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erſwaded them to do what they did; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat the only way of preſerving our ſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd all we had about us, was by keeping it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ogether, and making the Ship the ſole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lace of Retreat and Refuge. Beſides, I ever <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urred them up to action, expreſſing daily <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he hopes I had of getting out; foreſeeing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat by their ſitting altogether by the fire, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey might grow diſeaſed and unfit for ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ice: on the contrary, that exerciſe, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xpoſing themſelves to the air frequently, would render them more Hardy and Heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hy.</p>
            <p n="17">17th, <hi>Wedneſday.</hi> 'Twas handſome wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her of Wind, and that at N. W. but with much Snow, yet we hauled out our Sheat Anchor again.</p>
            <p n="18">18th, <hi>Thurſday.</hi> For wind as before. I began now to conſider, that the Froſt might render our Iron Anchors ſo brittle, as to make our Dependance on them not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure. Thereupon taking with me ſome men aſhore with Iron Crows and Shovels, I endeavoured to break ground; which
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:50975:24"/> when I found poſſible, I ordered the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penter to cut a new Mizen-Maſt I had on Board, not yet uſed. Of the biggeſt end I took twelve foot, and (after a hole of 7 foot deep had been digged, with no ſmall Labour) I placed it, filling the hole with Earth, Stones, and Water, which being frozen, might the better fix it, as a poſt for a Cable to be faſtned to. But that night I forbore uſing it; being not willing to ſhake it, before it was fully eſtabliſhed. The little Light we had was not above 5 hours continuance.</p>
            <p>The 19th, <hi>Friday.</hi> It blew ſtrongly from the S. S. Eaſt, and held very clear. As ſoon as it was light I got my beſt Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er-Cable hauled up; I took alſo a peice of a Junck Cable about twenty Fathom long, and made it faſt to the Stake above menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned (which ſtood off to the S. and by W.) and ſeaſed an Eye at the other end. Then I took one end of my beſt Bower Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, (the other being faſt to the Anchor) and after I had made an Eye on that alſo, with two Louff-Tackles, I brought both as near as I could together, which was within 3 fathom, and ſeaſed them.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:50975:24"/>
            <p>This I had ſcarce done, but there came down ſo much Wind at S. S. E. that we feared all would have been pulled to pieces: But every thing holding ſo well, our men could not but acknowledge the hand of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence in what had been done that day: For hereby we were preſerved, not only then, but all the Winter.</p>
            <p n="20">20th <hi>Saturday.</hi> By the firſt light of our ſlender day, we perceived our Skiffe full of water at our Stern, which we hoiſted on Board to mend again. You muſt note we could keep no Night Watch; our men not being able to walk the Deck half an hour for Cold.</p>
            <p>I now made ſtrict Enquiry into the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity we had of Peaſe left, getting a Barrel out, and meaſuring them. Of theſe after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward I delivered out 4 Quarts a day for all our Ships Company, being 24 men and Boys, and this I did four days in a week. I like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe made ſearch into our other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, and found we had 530 pieces of Beef, of four pound each. Of Fiſh we had but 6 days left; allowing four North-Sea Cods a day: nine days Flower and Cheeſe; allowing two pound of Cheeſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:50975:25"/> a day, for four men, with a Kettle of Haſty Pudding, for the whole Ships com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; that being the beſt way of uſing my Flower. Seeing now little hopes of getting home before <hi>March</hi> at the ſooneſt, we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, that Store muſt be kept for the Sea, when it ſhould pleaſe God to ſend us thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; nor had we reaſonable expectation of getting relief in this place.</p>
            <p n="21">21ſt <hi>Sunday.</hi> One of our Boys com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of his Feet being ſore, our Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon immediately viewing them, found the effect of the Froſt there up to his Ankles; eſpecially one very dangerouſly: but by his Skill and Diligence, he recovered them in Ten Days.</p>
            <p n="22">22d <hi>Monday.</hi> It proving fair, we fetch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Boat of Wood; great quantities of which we burnt every day. And here it will not be amiſs to mention our manner of keeping Fire. I cauſed the Iron Hearth in the Fore-Caſtle to be brought into the Steerage, and ordered the Carpenter to make a Hearth as big as conveniently could ſtand in the Fore Caſtle; which was five foot nine inches ſquare every way. Then I ſent aſhore for as much Clay, and as many
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:50975:25"/> Stones as filled it up: this was ſufficient to accommodate ſixteen men ſitting cloſe about it at once. Moreover, I directed the Cooper for making a Chimney to the Steerage, in the manner following, <hi>viz.</hi> by ſtaving an empty Butt or Pipe, and reducing the ſtaves at one end, to the breadth of two inches each, ſo that being Hoopt again, it exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not the wideneſs of a Firkin at the Top, keeping the former breadth or capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city in the middle, ſtill enlarging or ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more open at the bottom. The di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances or interſtices there between the Staves, we filled with pieces of Wood, and made all tight with Clay and Stones; which when we had ſo finiſhed, we placed upon the Grating. This made the Steerage very warm; but in all the time we kept Fire there, we were obliged to keep the door open for admittance of Wind, to give the Smoak vent.</p>
            <p>About eight this night the Wind came to the S. S. E. with Snow and hard Froſt; but at two in the Morning, there was clear good weather.</p>
            <p n="23">23d <hi>Tueſday.</hi> We had no foul weather, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t ſo cloſe, that we could ſcarce call that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:50975:26"/> Light we had day. However we made ſhift to get a Boat of Wood, being in great fear of loſing the day wholly.</p>
            <p>At eight at night it blew from the S. S. E. but towards midnight the wind came more to the Eaſtward, with handſome wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p n="24">24th <hi>Wedneſday.</hi> It proved fair and clear, the Wind Southerly. We cleared the Deck of Snow and Ice, which was grown a foot thick near the Scuppers. 'Twas ſometimes ſquauly, but at eventide I ſaw the Northern Glance: That is, a ſtream of light enlightening all the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſphere, ſo as one may read very well with it. 'Tis of a Pale-Yellow or Buff-Colour, like the Inmoſt Circle of the Rain-bow, appearing for a Quarter of an hour, then vaniſhing and renewing it ſelf again, by intervals during the ſpace of five or ſix hours. Sometimes this Meteor ſeems a bright nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble moving Cloud; at another time two of them, ruſhing and encountring one another, like Armies engaged: and now and then I have thought with a grumbling noiſe akin to Thunder. We reckon the Froſt to occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion them, and whatever Reflects or E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitts the light in that manner, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:50975:26"/> be far from the Eye, being ſo plainly to be diſcerned, and ſo exceeding ſwift.</p>
            <p n="25">25th <hi>Thurſday.</hi> It being fair, I endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to clear the Hawſe, but there was ſo much Ice upon the Cables, I could not do it. This day two of my men went up the Hills, but wanted Light to make a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery.</p>
            <p n="26">26th <hi>Friday.</hi> Still fair and clear, and by the Light we had, I brought my beſt Bower Cable, to the Stake on ſhore, and ſerved it well with old Ropes, to prevent its cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing: the Wind at E. N. E. and freezing hard.</p>
            <p>The 27th <hi>Saturday.</hi> It proved fair and Calm, with ſome little Snow. I got a boat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>load of Water; and ſerved all our Cables to prevent Chafing, both aſhore and at the Hawſe.</p>
            <p>I had complaint made me, that ſome had ſtoln Fiſh and broiled it; but upon ſtrict enquiry, I found ſuch a thing could not be done privately: by reaſon our men ſat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly round the Hearth in the Fore-Caſtle, from 6 or 7 in the Morning till 8 at night;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:50975:27"/> at which hour, or ſoon after, I ever cauſed the Fire to be put out, fearing the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual keeping it might endanger the Ship, or occaſion other Diſorders. Nevertheleſs I cauſed the Fiſh that hung overboard for watering, to be hauled in, and viewing it well, by the manner of it, I judged that the pieces diminiſhed, were not cut off with a Knife, bur rather ſeemed bitten by ſome living Creature; which I ſuppoſed might be a Seal, that I had ſeen ſometimes about the Ship. So I put the Salt-fiſh into a Bag, and by a Line hung it over the Ship for freſhning: And in the mean time I got a great Shark-hook, and baited it with a piece of the ſame; hanging it a foot under water, in a place where the Seal uſed to ſhow himſelf. I ſtood upon the Watch; and juſt as it was dark, the Seal came and took it, making a buſtling at the ſide of the Ship. I preſently took hold of the Rope, to which it was faſtned, and found it too heavy for me, which made me call for help; but before it came he got looſe, and I ſaw him ſet his Feet to the Ships ſide, and fling himſelf off: After this we ſaw him no more in the Bay.</p>
            <p n="28">
               <pb facs="tcp:50975:27"/>28th <hi>Sunday.</hi> It was ſtill Calm, but with more Snow and cloſe weather.</p>
            <p n="29">29th <hi>Monday.</hi> I hauled my Sheat-An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor further out, the Wind at W. S. W. blowing freſh with Snow; but at 4 at night it began to Thaw conſiderably. I then ſhared all the Bread in the bread-Room, being but 5 pound and a half for each man.</p>
            <p n="30">30th <hi>Tueſday,</hi> It froze hard again, even our Beer between Decks; ſo that our Men could get nothing but water to drink, which had not ſtood above 12 hours, but became all Ice. I conſidered, that for them to drink warm water, might not be ſo good for their Stomachs, and to ſtave our Casks, would be of ill Conſequence for us, when we ſhould have occaſion for them, at our going to Sea. I then brought up a Cask of my own Honey, of which I diſtributed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 2 pound and a quarter to each Man, for them to boil in their Water, to make a kind of Mead withal. This they drank, and were not offended with the Ice in their Mouths as before. The Wind all this day at S. S. Eaſt, and the Froſt ſo exceſſive, that we feared the Spring Heads would e're long
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:50975:28"/> fail us, ſo that we beſtirred our ſelves for a Boat load of Water.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>December</hi> the 1ſt <hi>Wedneſday.</hi> It proved fair, which encouraged me to ſend my Mate in the Boat up the <hi>Fuel,</hi> even before it was light; chiefly to ſee if there were any An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choring places for us to make uſe of, in caſe we ſhould put out, and not be able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain our Harbour. He returned and brought word, that he ſaw only two Iſlands on the Weſt ſide, and that the <hi>Fuel</hi> ran up a great way very wide, where they had much Wind: But where the Ship lay, we found little all day.</p>
            <p n="2">2d <hi>Thurſday.</hi> 'Twas fair weather of Wind out of the S. Eaſt corner, but froze hard all day, with ſome Snow. You muſt know, our brighteſt time now at noon, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded not the light that comes an hour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Sun riſe, in an Equinoctial day in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3d <hi>Friday.</hi> The Wind as before, and pretty calm ſtill, but freezing exceeding hard. Howbeit we went aſhore for Wood, of which we got not above two thirds of a Boat full; ſo ſhort was our day, and this
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:50975:28"/> eſpecially ſo very cloſe, that we could not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſcern the tops of the Hills, all that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght.</p>
            <p>The 4th, <hi>Saturday.</hi> The Wind kept at S. E. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir, and freezing hard, but towards night <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me Snow. It was light now but 3 hours <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd a half; as I obſerved by my Watch, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> my warm Pocket went well, and (to my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eat Comfort) kept its integrity in the worſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> times.</p>
            <p>The 5, <hi>Sunday.</hi> We had handſome weather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Wind with ſome Snow, and about 3 at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght a ſmall thaw.</p>
            <p>The 6th, <hi>Monday.</hi> Being moderate weather, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut cloſe and freezing) we fetched a Boat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Water. All our men went aſhore; ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith Guns, and among them they ſhot a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hite Partridge, which was very good Meat; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e reſt employed themſelves in gathering <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſcles, Periwinkles, and Dills. Theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lls are dark brown Weeds, growing and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nging upon the Rocks, and to be come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> while low Water: a ſort of Sea Plant or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rb, common enough in the North of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>nd,</hi> but more frequent in <hi>Scotland.</hi> There, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m told, they are eaten raw; but by boil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:50975:29"/> they become ſoft, and look greene taſting not much unlike a Colewort. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> way of dreſſing them, was firſt to boil th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in freſh water, which took away the Sal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſs natural to them; and after that boilin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them again in our Beef Broth, they ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plied the place of a Sallet, to eat with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Beef.</p>
            <p>By ſome <hi>Scottiſh</hi> men on board, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> were happily inſtructed in the uſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> theſe.</p>
            <p>The 7th, <hi>Tueſday.</hi> It proved fair abo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> head, the Wind S.S.E. but freezing very ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> We got ſome empty Cask from betwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Decks to fill them, fearing more and mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to depend upon the Springs. For our m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were lately at a great loſs for them, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> found it difficult digging in the Ice. The way was, when they went for Water, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> obſerve the Drains upon the Shore, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> along the ſunken or depreſſed places in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Snow, which were formed from the Springs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the upper Grounds, joining in their Deſce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and making Gutters, ſome with ſtrea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> large enough to turn a little Mill. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Channels were covered with Ice like a Ceili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> under which the Water ran freely, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:50975:29"/> come at it, they were forced to dig through <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>now, and break through Ice, to dip in their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owls and fill their Pails; which when full <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> carried to the Boat, where the Hog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ead ſtood with open heads to receive them. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> notwithſtanding they made all poſſible <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſte aboard, and had not above a furlong <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o Row, by that time they got to the Ship, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Water would be covered with a pretty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hick Ice. The Pails too thereby, were ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rozen both within and without, as to weigh much more, and hold much leſs; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd we were forced to thaw them conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ally, for a new days ſervice.</p>
            <p>The 8th, <hi>Wedneſday.</hi> We had it fair and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eat, with a ſmall Thaw, the Wind We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>erly. We filled ſome Water, and put it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>own into the Hold.</p>
            <p>The 9th, <hi>Thurſday.</hi> We had very fair wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er and ſo warm, as to make a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Thaw: The Wind W. S. W.</p>
            <p>The 10th, <hi>Friday.</hi> 'Twas fair over head, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oze exceeding hard; we fetched a Boat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>d of Water. Our Men thought it good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ews, when I told them this was the Short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> Day, and now we ſhould make our
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:50975:30"/> ſelves ready for the Sea, as faſt as poſſib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we could. In order thereto, I gave my chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Mate directions, for Rowing up the <hi>Fuel</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the morrow, to take a full view of the firſt B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we came by. This was matter of Enco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ragement to them, and kept them in action tho I did it with little hopes of ſudd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Benefit thereby.</p>
            <p>The 11, <hi>Saturday.</hi> It proving fair I ſent t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Boat into the outermoſt Bay to view it, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> get acquainted with ſome place of ſhelte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that we might make uſe of, in caſe w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhould not be able to regain the Harbour, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> proceed at our firſt putting out. They r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turned and brought me word, there was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> good Road within an Iſland that lay in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Bay: which made me reſolve, if the weath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> held open, that we could work, to ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> out for the Sea by Moonlight.</p>
            <p>The 12th, <hi>Sunday.</hi> Was a fair day, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Wind at S. W.</p>
            <p>The 13, <hi>Monday.</hi> It continuing fair weathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we got up our Spritſail-Yard and Fore-Ya<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> croſs again; filled a Boat Load of Wate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and got two Wouldens on our Rudder Hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Wind Eaſterly.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:50975:30"/>
            <p>The 14th, <hi>Tueſday.</hi> So cloſe all day, as to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſcarce good Twilight. A young Man in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir Company took a Bible of a ſmall print, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y if he could read in it, but could not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m his Letters at twelve at noon. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er, I got up both my Top-Maſts and Main <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ard croſs, hoiſed my Mizen yard, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uled aboard one of my Haulſers: The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ind at W. S. W.</p>
            <p>The 15th, <hi>Wedneſday.</hi> We had as little light <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is Day as the Day before, with uncertain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eather, ſometimes blowing freſh and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mes Calm; but the Scudd came very ſwift <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t of the Weſt S. W. all day: we got but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lf a Boat load of Wood. At 9 at night <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> blew a Storm at N. W. with much Snow, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat we were forced to ſtrike our Yards <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd Top-Maſts, as faſt as we could.</p>
            <p>The 16th, <hi>Thurſday.</hi> It continued blowing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ard at W.N.W. Snowing much, and freezing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t ſo extravagant a rate, that every thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecame Ice, that was capable of being made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>The 17th, <hi>Friday.</hi> It blew hard at S. S. E. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith more Snow: and at 3 at night, or in
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:50975:31"/> the after part of the day (as you will plea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to call it,) it proved a ſtorm out of the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> point.</p>
            <p>The 18, <hi>Saturday.</hi> The Wind was all South<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>erly, blowing hard, and freezing ſeverely<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but dry over head. Bad as it was, we fetch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed a Boat load of Wood, and ſome wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> aſhore in the Skiff and got Periwinkles. 'Twa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtrange how theſe little Creatures coul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> live, and endure ſo much Froſt: for as ſoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as the Water was gone from them, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> would ſoon be covered with Ice, but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> returning Tide melted it. Theſe we too off the Shore at low water, and brough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them on Board, where we boiled them i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Shells, and picked out the Snail, or tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> part that was Meat.</p>
            <p>The 19th, <hi>Sunday.</hi> It blew hard at S.S.W<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with much Snow and hard Froſt.</p>
            <p>The 20th, <hi>Monday.</hi> It blew deſperately har<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at N. E. with much Snow and ſevere Froſt Our day at this time was not 4 hours and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> half long.</p>
            <p>The 21ſt, <hi>Tueſday.</hi> In the Morning the Wind was at N. W. at Noon all Northerly; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:50975:31"/> night N. E. with little Snow but continued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſt. About this time I obſerved the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cooping or Emptying of the Boat, was a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hing of too great Labour for the Boys to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o; ſo I ordered the Men to take their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urns. This was very grievous to them; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in a nights time it would be half full <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f Snow, and the Water in the bottom fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en pretty thick: ſo that they muſt firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hrow out the Snow, then break a hole in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Ice, and by that ſcoop out the Water, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd at laſt take away the Ice with Shovels. The Stem of the Boat too, would in that time be covered four or five Inches thick with Ice, and about the edge of the Water alſo; which we were forced to break off with Mauls, or Wooden Beetles. During this, our people ſuffered ſo exceedingly, as to come aboard with their Limbs almoſt ſtiff with Cold, and their Hair ſo frozen, as to hang with large Icycles, in the faſhion of great Taggs.</p>
            <p>The 22d, <hi>Wedneſday.</hi> Cloſe Snowy wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all day, and the Wind Weſterly; but by that time it was quite dark, it came to the N. E. blowing freſh. Here I think it proper to ſet down my Conſtant Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Sky towards the North Pole,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:50975:32"/> which I had made daily for four weeks la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> paſt: <hi>viz.</hi> That even during that time o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Light we called Day, it continued alway<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> black, as if it were a dark Cloud forerun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning a Squaul. It reached from N. W. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> N. E. in the form of a Rain-bow, the Art<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> elevated fifteen or twenty Degrees. Whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> made me conclude, that ſomething farthe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the North, there muſt be a continua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> night all that while.</p>
            <p>The 23d, <hi>Thurſday.</hi> The morning wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fair, but by noon the air was thick with Snow. I got a Boat load of Water, and ſome Wood; and gave every man two pound and a quarter of Honey, to make drink againſt <hi>Chriſtmas.</hi> I find no notice of Wind taken this day, and likewiſe of ſome few before; but I am aſſured it was too dark to think of ſtirring: we could not ſee to eat our meat at noon without Candles, of which we conſumed plenty, bringing about 500 weight from <hi>Ruſſia:</hi> for though we kept two Lamps burning day and night, we yet uſed Candles upon frequent and moving occaſions.</p>
            <p>The 24th, <hi>Friday.</hi> It proved fair and clear, the Froſt not exceſſive; ſo that we
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:50975:32"/> cleaned our Decks from Snow and Ice. The Wind was Northerly all day, but to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards night it came to the Eaſt. Our men being very melancholy, to think of their Friends at home providing good chear, I told them they ſhould not pinch on the day following; and accordingly ordered every Meſs ſhould have full allowance. This put an end to that kind of diſcourſe, and they ſeemed pleaſed with the expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſuch a Feaſt; but thought not of<note n="*" place="bottom">Sea term for pinching the Belly.</note> Hauling Sharp for it afterward.</p>
            <p>The 25th, <hi>Saturday.</hi> Being <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> day, in the former part of the day we had good weather, the Wind at S. W.; but for the latter part it blowed and ſnowed. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Dinner, I ſpared out of my own ſtore, to every two men, a Bottle of Strong Beer, which they took thankfully, and made their hearts truly glad. About ſix at night, as I was walking upon the Deck, I obſerved it ſo bright for a quarter of an hour, that we had it no lighter for ſome days at Noon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſince our being here. This muſt be from ſome Northern Glance; the more remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble then, as unuſual in cloſe weather.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:50975:33"/>
            <p>The 26th, <hi>Sunday.</hi> It proved indifferent fair, with ſmall Snow like rain; that is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming drops of water, upon its a lighting or falling upon the Deck: the Wind at S. W.</p>
            <p>The 27th, <hi>Monday.</hi> I fetched a Boat of Water, the weather being fair and calm. This day I took up a Hogſhead of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants Honey, and ſhared it equally, giving each man his part, to make Mead as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly.</p>
            <p>The 28th, <hi>Tueſday.</hi> The laſt night was warm, and a ſmall Thaw we had: the day held fair, and the night enſuing continued Calm.</p>
            <p>The 29th, <hi>Wedneſday.</hi> Still over head fair enough, but it froze again exceſſive hard: The Wind at N. E. The day now was 5 hours long, and at Noon time we ſaw it was perfect day.</p>
            <p>The 30th, <hi>Thurſday.</hi> It blew hard at W. S. W. with ſome Snow. I ſent the long Boat a Wooding, and 3 hands in the Skiff for Water; and the latter I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied, in order to viſit the inſide
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:50975:33"/> of thoſe Houſes, that were juſt by us, which our men diſcovered ſoon after our coming into this Bay or Cove. Here were dwelling Houſes for 3 Families, as near as I could gueſs, each having another for Cattle adjoyning, and one for drying of Fiſh, which was open like a Cage, with Poles lying acroſs. I carried things with me, for clearing the way to the Doors from Snow; and approaching them, I found the dwelling Houſes were built above 5 foot from the Ground, and 12 foot broad, in form round. The Walls were made of Stones, and Moſs between them, inſtead of Morter, and Roofed with the ſame, by the help of Rafters or Split Trees, their lower ends reſting upon the wall, and their upper joining at the top againſt a hollow Stone, which ſerved both for Chimney and Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow. And for a Hearth there was a flat Stone, laid ſomewhat above the Ground; and on one ſide a Cabbin, big enough for two people to lye in, with ſome Straw in it there left, which I gueſſed was all their bedding. In one of them I found a Barrel of Rye Meal, but ſo bad as not to be uſed for Food. We met there with a piece of a Printed Book, with a form of Prayer therein, of the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Language; as one of our Men told us, who
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:50975:34"/> underſtood it, being by Birth of that Nation. In the Houſes for Cattle were Stalls and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions (of Sticks croſſing one another as Hurdles are made,) ſuch as are in Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Stables to part their Stone-Horſes; with Boards too at the Bottom. They were ſo ſmall, as to contain nothing bigger than Sheep or Goats; the latter being more frequent in the Neighbouring Countries: The doors of theſe Folds or Houſes, were not above 3 foot and a half high, and 2 in breadth; they were half full of Snow, ſo that no dung could be obſerved. To one houſe was an incloſure like a yard, with a Pond of Water, but frozen. Likewiſe there was a place diſcernable, where they hauled their Boat upon Land, when they had been a Fiſhing.</p>
            <p>The 31ſt, <hi>Friday.</hi> In the Morning it blew hard at S. W. but the latter part of the day was very warm, and it fell a Raining, and thawed very much. This made us wiſh for a Light Moon, to be going with.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>January</hi> the 1ſt, <hi>Saturday.</hi> It blew hard at Weſt, but warm to admiration, ſo as to make a very great Thaw: even the tops of ſeveral ſmall Hills, that laid under the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:50975:34"/> higher ones, became bare, and clear of Snow. Withal a great deal of Snow, that lay upon many parts of the Ship, was melted off. At the ſame time came a great Sea into the Bay where we lay, breaking very high at the Harbours mouth; but towards night the Wind was at W. N. W.</p>
            <p>The 2d, <hi>Sunday.</hi> The Wind was at S. W. blowing hard. It continued ſtill thawing all this 24 hours.</p>
            <p>The 3d, <hi>Monday.</hi> We had a warm, fair, and dry day, with little Wind, and that at S. W. This was the firſt day we could open any Sail, ſince we came in here: ſo we opened our Mainſail to Air it, and found no harm done to it, notwithſtanding it had continued ſo long furled up, which we greatly feared before. We got a Boat of Water too.</p>
            <p>The 4th, <hi>Tueſday.</hi> Still fair over Head, and moderate as to Wind, which was at the S. S. W. but the Froſt had made its Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn. I ſent the Boat into the <hi>Fuel,</hi> to ſee if they could take any Fiſh; but they got none. One Hogſhead of Water more they got filled, and put between Decks.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:50975:35"/>
            <p>The 5th, <hi>Wedneſday.</hi> It blew freſh Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly, with ſome ſmall Snow, and froze hard again. I ſent my Men a Wooding, where they could not but obſerve, what al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration the late open weather had made upon the Trees, diſpoſing them to flouriſh, by moiſtening their Bark, and opening their Budds conſiderably; which the returning cold had nipt again. Likewiſe upon the Hills that were bare by the Thaw, they found plenty of Green Juniper, of which they gathered, and brought on board a great many Branches. Withal they peeled off the Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Bark of the Willow-like Tree, and bound it up in ſeveral Bundles, to hang near the Fire and dry, for an intended uſe. This over and above their Load of Wood, which they made good.</p>
            <p>The 6th, <hi>Thurſday.</hi> 'Twas very fair over head, but blowing pretty hard at S. S. W. the Froſt too encreaſing. Yet they made ſhift to get a Boat of Wood, with more Juniper, and quantity of Bark as before.</p>
            <p>The 7th, <hi>Friday.</hi> It proved very bad weather, the Wind high at N. W. and much Snow again. This days confinement gave
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:50975:35"/> our people leiſure, to advance a new project, and make tryal of what they had got to ſupply the want of Tobacco; with which, had they been ſufficiently ſtockt, it would have been a great Relief to them, and a choice entertainment. For my own part, I had juſt enough to allow my ſelf 3 or 4 Pipes in a day, and could not find in my heart to ſpare any to my beſt Friend<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Though it could not but greive my Spirit to ſee one Smoaking inſtead of it, meer Rags of Fuſtian torn from a Coat-pocket. But this was before they found out the uſe of ſomething more like it, being parts of dryed Plants: I mean the tops of Juniper before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, and the Willow Bark dryed. Theſe they now began to ſhred ſmall with a Knife, and mix together in proportions according to each mans fancy, and to fill their Pipes therewith. All that take To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco know theſe have no agreement with the other, as to virtue and effects; nor yield the like pleaſure or benefit: But the Smoak I am ſure was not ungrateful, and poſſibly not unwholeſom, both for the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers and Company; and in my opinion, it was no mean Invention, in ſuch extream ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:50975:36"/>
            <p>The 8th, <hi>Saturday.</hi> The weather as bad as the day before, both of Wind and Snow, and freezing hard. However, we cleared our Decks of Snow and Ice, and ſtowed what Wood we could ſpare out of the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtle and Steerage, to make fit for the Sea, having hopes that it would pleaſe God to give us opportunity, by this light Moon.</p>
            <p>The 9th, <hi>Sunday.</hi> The night paſt was very ſtormy, blowing hard ſtill in the Morning at S. S. E. with exceſſive Froſt and ſome Snow: but towards noon the weather mended in all reſpects.</p>
            <p>The 10th, <hi>Monday.</hi> We had a Storm but of the N. W. violent and furious, and I think with the moſt Wind that ever I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in my Life, though I have uſed the Sea theſe 38 years. It Snowed very hard withal, and froze at a great rate, inſomuch, that the forepart of the Ship, by the daſhing of the water againſt her, and the mounting of the Foam by the Tempeſt, had nothing but what was covered with Ice.</p>
            <p>The 11th, <hi>Tueſday.</hi> It continued blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hard at N. W. with Snow and hard
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:50975:36"/> Froſt. The night paſt we loſt 13 pieces of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eef, as they hung a watering, which at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat time was a great mortification to us. For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur way was to put our Beef into a Wicker-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>amper, and hang it by a Rope at the Ships <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de two foot under water; now the Rope <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>athering a Quantity of Ice, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſive Wind giving the Ship ſome Motion, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was thereby chafed aſunder, and the Beef <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t drop. It is to be obſerved; that we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould not freſhen our Meat after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er uſual at Sea, by putting the ſame into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Tub of Sea-water; for that would have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>een all Ice in a few hours, and the fleſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill as hard and ſalt as before: the Wicker-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>amper too, was to preſerve it from Vora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ious Fiſhes, as the Seal before ſpoken of.</p>
            <p>The 12th, <hi>Wedneſday.</hi> It blew freſh at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. S. W. and froze ſmartly. We got our Warp Anchor and two Haulſers on board, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd made four pair of Graplines or Creep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs, with which we went to try if we could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lank the Hamper, and recover the Beef we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſt two nights before; but we were not ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ucky as to light upon it.</p>
            <p>But my Mate in holding the Line, while <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e was creeping or ſearching for the Hamper,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:50975:37"/> got the Froſt in his Fingers, inſomuch tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the next day morning, he found Bliſters riſen upon them and his Thumbs, as if they had been ſcalded. And after the water wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> let out by opening them, his hands were ſo raw, as to make him uncapable of going a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wooding.</p>
            <p>The 13th, <hi>Thurſday.</hi> The Wind was a S. E. and moderate enough, but the cold a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> rigorous as at any time before, and this day with a conſiderable Rime Froſt. Howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, we got a Boat load of Wood; bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> when our Men came aboard, they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained much of the Froſt being got into their Feet and Hands; ſome only bliſtered others turned black, and without feeling Our Chirurgeon opened the Bliſters, and by Fomentations and other applications, he recovered them; and where it was turned black, he cut off the dead and ſenſeleſs part, and healed them after ſome time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> wherein he manifeſted himſelf to have a good underſtanding in his buſineſs, by the ſucceſs he had; ſeeing none had any loſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of an entire part or joint, but purely of what Fleſh or Skin was mortify'd before he ſaw it: and they all became ſerviceable by that time I got home, or ſoon after. In juſtice
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:50975:37"/> and gratitude I am obliged to mention his name; <hi>WILLIAM BROWN</hi> of <hi>Great Yarmouth,</hi> and educated there under his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the ſame profeſſion.</p>
            <p>The 14th, <hi>Friday.</hi> Fair and clear wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we had, but it froze ſo vehemently, that I durſt not let any man go out of the Ship, or do any work that day: Cheriſhing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd giving reſt to the diſabled, and reſerving the ſound.</p>
            <p>The 15th, <hi>Saturday.</hi> Still clear as the day before, but freezing exceeding hard: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Wind in the morning at N. E. but at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight S. E. with a violent ſtorm. At noon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e reckoned the Sun made his firſt bodily <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ppearance, in our part of the world, for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ear enſuing: The day 8 hours and a half <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ng.</p>
            <p>The 16th, <hi>Sunday.</hi> It blew hard at N. W. in the morning; at noon the Wind <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as at N. N. Eaſt, and freezing; but not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o hard as before.</p>
            <p>The 17th, <hi>Monday.</hi> We had much wind <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t N. VV. with ſome Snow; the Froſt too <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e look'd upon as leſs vehement than for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:50975:38"/>
            <p>The 18th, <hi>Tueſday.</hi> The morning was bluſtering and cloudy; the Wind at N. VV<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> At noon it cleared, and we ſaw the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beams gilding the tops of ſeveral Hills, to our great joy and comfort: For we had no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſeen Sun-ſhine before in ten weeks. Afte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> noon the Wind came to the N. E. fine wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: We got a boat load of wood, and two Hogſheads of water. The latter wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> difficult to come at, the Springs being al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> frozen up, only the run of the great Spring, we found gliding under the full Sea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mark.</p>
            <p>The 19th, <hi>Wedneſday.</hi> It was calm and good weather; I cauſed the Decks and Scuppers to be cleared of Ice and Snow: In doing which, we were forced to heat Crow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Iron red hot, and ſo by degrees mel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a way through the Scupper-holes, and fre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them from Ice. And with the ſame Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Axes, cut through and raiſe up the Ice upon the Decks, and to heave ove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> board. Notwithſtanding it froze extream hard at this time, yet we had warm hope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of getting to Sea; the Wind being at S. E.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:50975:38"/>
            <p>The 20th, <hi>Thurſday.</hi> The Wind was at W. S. W. and moderate: neither was it ſo cold as the day before; freezing no harder than it does in a hard Froſt in <hi>England.</hi> We hauled the Ship about twice, to clear the Hawſe: and in the afternoon went and got Periwinkles, Muſcles and Dills.</p>
            <p>The 21ſt, <hi>Friday.</hi> It blew hard at W. N W. but was very warm, ſo as to cauſe a ſmall thaw. We got a Boat load of Wood, and another of Water; and at the Edge of the ſhore, our men ſaw Eggs, one of which they pulled upon Land, with a long bent ſtick, and brought it on board. Theſe are likewiſe called Sea-Urchins, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſomewhat growing upon the Shells like Thorns, or the Briſtles upon the Land Hedge-hog. The ſhape is round and flattiſh, the ſhell thin, and the Briſtles eaſily rub off: For a further deſcription, I muſt refer the Reader to Authors, that treat of ſuch things. 'Twas good news for me to hear of them, knowing what benefit they might be to us; and therefore I cauſed a piece of Iron Hoop to be fixed to the end of a Pole, and made a Net like a Fiſhermans Lead-net, againſt the next day.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:50975:39"/>
            <p>The 22d, <hi>Saturday.</hi> The Wind was at Weſt S. W. the weather fair too, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different warm. We firſt cleared the Deck of the Wood brought in the day before, and ſtowed it down into the Hold, for a Sea ſtore. Afterward ſome went aſhore with the Pole and Net aforeſaid, and got ſtore of Eggs: while others went a Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, who ſhot only a ſmall Fowl calle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Greenland</hi> Pidgeon. I do not remember <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or the firſt two months and more after I came in here, I ever ſaw any but two Birds or Fowls flying, and they were two Crows of a Dun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> colour, not different from ours ſo called; and by ſome <hi>Royſton</hi>-Crows. Theſe flew often near the Ship, and at length were ſo tame, as to light upon our Deck: one of which our men ſhot, poor and lean as he was, and nothing but Skin, Bone and Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. But before I came away I ſaw ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of the <hi>Greenland</hi> Doves aforeſaid, and Fowls like what we call Kitties, pick up things at low water, which I gueſſed might be Periwinkles, and Sea Eggs eſpecially<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For one day, (though I have not ſet it down punctually, I bear it well in mind,) I went my ſelf aſhore, and a furlong up the Hills, I found the Shells of Sea Eggs, which
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:50975:39"/> I judged might have been carryed up by ſuch Birds. They are ſpecial good Food, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doubt not but the Birds ſuck out all their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nwards, though we eat only the yellow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>art like an Eggs yolk, and throw away the other white or jelly part. That we take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd put into a Sauce-pan, and pour to it ſome Beef Broth, which with a little Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſtrewed upon it, and ſtewed together, makes a very good Diſh.</p>
            <p>The 23d, <hi>Sunday.</hi> We had it fair and clear all day, the Wind Southerly, and the Froſt very moderate.</p>
            <p>The 24th, <hi>Monday.</hi> Still fair and clear, the Wind Southerly. We got our Kedge Anchor on Board, but much trouble had we to come at it. We were forced to dig through a great deal of Ice, and the ground it ſelf frozen deep, under which one flook had been long buryed. We ſhifted one of our ſmall Haulſers too, at the ſtake where the Cable was faſt: got both our Top-maſts up, hoiſted our Mizen-yard, and got our Fore-yards up, with an intent to be jog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging; but before night, it began to blow at S. S. W.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:50975:40"/>
            <p>The 25th, <hi>Tueſday.</hi> It blew very hard, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that I was forced to ſtrike both Top<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſts, and lower all down again. Beſides, it froze extreamly hard all this 24 hours. Thus were we fatally baulked, and our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of ſtirring put a ſtop to, when we had Proviſion enough left, to go to Sea with; I can't ſay without great hazard of want, and danger of weather, could we have held on our purpoſe.</p>
            <p>The 26th, <hi>Wedneſday.</hi> It continued ſtill blowing, and the Wind all Southerly, ſo that at certain times, when the blaſts came violently off the Hills, notwithſtanding the Hawſe was very foul and thick frozen, yet the Cable would be pulled ſtark out of the Water. The Haulſer too at the ſtake on ſhore, having a great weight of Ice upon it, would nevertheleſs be ſtiff-ſtrained above the Water, as level as that of a Rope-dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, when it is made fit to walk upon. It being to admiration, that the Stake, Cable and Haulſers ſhould hold.</p>
            <p>The 27th, <hi>Thurſday.</hi> The Wind and weather ſtill the ſame as the day before; blowing fiercely, but clear over head, and freezing at a great rate.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:50975:40"/>
            <p>The 28th, <hi>Friday.</hi> The Wind kept its place, but grew more moderate; the Froſt ſtill exceſſive: However I got a boat load of water, and another of wood.</p>
            <p>The 29th, <hi>Saturday.</hi> It blew ſmartly out of the South, and froze ſo extraordinary hard, that the water we brought on board the day before, was a ſolid Body of Ice. For having occaſion to Brew that morning, (it being late before the water came on board over night) I cauſed one of the Hog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheads to be digged into, to ſee if any wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter could be found in the Cask; and in the midſt there might be the quantity of about two Gallons lying in a hole of the depth of 14 inches, and 3 inches width: of that I made Mead, which proved excellent good, and ſome of the very ſame, I brought with me to <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 30th, <hi>Sunday.</hi> It blew a hard Gale at S. by E. freezing withal; but not ſo hard as two days before.</p>
            <p>The 31ſt, <hi>Monday.</hi> We had as much Wind as the day before, and from the ſame point; but dry overhead, and freezing to
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:50975:41"/> extremity. There was a Hogſhead that ſtood an end upon the Deck, full of Water with its head open, which froze gradually downward, ſo as to force the bottom out, and raiſe the Cask three inches from the place it ſtood on: and became a whole Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumn or Solid Body of Ice. Another at the ſame time that laid along with its Bung open, froze in the like manner, burſting open the undermoſt ſtaff upon which it reſted. I leave to the Reader to aſſign the natural reaſon of this, only taking along with him this remark; that it lay upon a pretty thick Ice that covered the Deck. How long they had been both filled I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay punctually: the firſt might be one of them brought on Board the <hi>Friday</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; the other poſſibly have lain longer, as deſigned for a Sea ſtore. This brings into conſideration the daily toil our Cook had, with an Iron Crow to break aſunder Lumps of Ice to put into the Pot. In doing which he was obliged to arm his Hands with Furr Gloves and Mittens; otherwiſe the Iron would have cleaved to his Fingers and carryed the Skin along with it. The ſame Cloathing or defence our men conſtantly uſed, not only abroad in Wooding and Watering, but alſo in their work aboard,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:50975:41"/> as handling the Ropes, or whatever elſe they touched or moved. Over and above, when they went in the Boat upon frequent expeditions, whether for carrying out, or weighing of Anchors, or going aſhore for the many purpoſes before-cited, they put on their <hi>Ruſſia</hi>-Boots, which were wide like thoſe worn by Fiſhermen, and lined with Bears-skin. Theſe they were all fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with, but two or three, who were glad to ſupply the want of them, by tying old pieces of Canvas about their Legs, and over their Feet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>February</hi> the firſt, <hi>Tueſday.</hi> It continued ſtill blowing hard at S. by E. clear withal; and about noon we ſaw the Sun ſhine into the mouth of the Harbour. He might ſhew the whole of his face, but little of his power; for it froze ſo exceſſively this day, that the Ice hung upon the Ship in ſome places full two foot thick, and at the edge of the Water it was of a great breadth. So that the Ship having a ſmall motion, made ſuch a noiſe, that the night before we could not ſleep for it. To prevent which, we hauled the Long-boat about the ſides, and with two great Beetles or Mauls broke it off: and ſometimes a piece
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:50975:42"/> of half a Tun weight would drop at once.</p>
            <p>The 2d, <hi>Wedneſday.</hi> It blew hard at South, with clear weather, but froze ſo very hard, that now all the Cables were paſt handling; which mightily diſcouraged us, and almoſt ſtifled all thoughts of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. To mention all the Diſcourſes our people had at times, and upon ſeveral oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences, would fill a bigger Volume; and a great many more I had ſet down, had it not been ſo great a trouble to write. 'Twas vexatious enough to get my Ink ready for uſe, and no leſs to keep it ſo; a Boy being forced to thaw it, as oft as I had occaſion to dip my Pen.</p>
            <p>The 3d, <hi>Thurſday.</hi> All the night paſt ſtormy, and the Wind Southerly, but it froze not ſo hard as the day before; we got a Boat load of Wood, and another of Water. As moderate as the weather was for cold, poſſibly on ſuch a day, we might get the Water on board in the Hogſheads, with little or no Ice on the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face of it; but after ſtanding half an hour upon Deck, we ſhould have it thick enough to bear an empty Pipe. This was a warm day
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:50975:42"/> comparatively, I ſay, and cheriſhed our dying hopes of getting from this place; and towards night we got up our Fore Top-Maſts, Fore Yard and Mizen Yard, to be in a readineſs for the Sea.</p>
            <p>The 4th, <hi>Friday.</hi> In the morning it blew a hard ſtorm at South, ſo that I was compelled once more to ſtrike our Yards and Top-maſts: But towards night the Wind eaſed, and we got our Stream Cable on board; leaving a piece of twenty fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thom behind us, ſo deep buried under the Ice on ſhore, as not to be got out.</p>
            <p>The 5th, <hi>Saturday.</hi> The day began with fine weather, the Wind at S. S. W. Our men diſcovered Scallop-ſhells near the Ship, but they lay in deep water. I cauſed a broad flat piece of Iron to be bent like a Dredge to fiſh for Oyſters with, and ordered a Bag to be made to it of Rope Yarn: and that night we went a dragging, and got ſixteen Scallops, which were very good Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als. I brought home with me ſome of theſe, and ſeveral other Shells, of which I careleſsly diſpoſed of, or loſt the moſt part: But when I waited upon that ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and worthy perſon Mr <hi>James Petiver,</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:50975:43"/> Apothecary in <hi>Alderſgate-ſtreet,</hi> and Fellow of the Royal Society, to preſent him with thoſe few I had remaining; from them and others he ſhewed me, I remembred they were almoſt all of ſuch kinds as are found about <hi>England.</hi> And by him I was further informed, that the general <hi>Engliſh</hi> names I had given to them were not impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: More diſtinctly he told me they were Periwinkles, Wilks, <hi>Scarborough</hi> Couvins, Limpets, Muſcles, Cockles, Sea Eggs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Oyſter-ſhells too I ſaw here and there, but not one whole, with the Inwards or Meat in it. I left with him likewiſe a piece or two of Coral, got when we dragged for theſe Shell Animals; having ſaved greater variety of the ſame, which an unlucky Boy threw over-board. Moreover, ſome Slate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Stones; and theſe I obſerved there of various colours, which when we held a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Grindſtone, tinged the water (it turned in) ſtrongly of the ſame colour. And in ſome Colour-ſhops where I expoſed them here in <hi>London,</hi> they concluded them fit for Painters uſe, and of good value. So that this wretched Country was not deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of all Humane Food or Commodity: and had I been there in a ſeaſon when the Snow was gone, much more might have
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:50975:43"/> been obſerved; or even then, had I made it more my buſineſs to diſcover what was odd or rare. Towards night the Wind came to the N. N. W. blowing hard and ſnowing.</p>
            <p>The 6th, <hi>Sunday.</hi> It proved fair and clear, till three in the afternoon; then the Wind ſhifted from the N. W. to South, and began to blow and overcaſt.</p>
            <p>The 7th, <hi>Monday.</hi> It blew hard in the morning at N. N. Weſt, and from thence the Wind ſhifted to W. S. W. I took now into further conſideration the quantity of proviſion I had left, and finding not above 203 pieces of Beef, and Peaſe proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and ſeeing no likelihood of getting any other relief while we ſtay'd here, than what we had met with, I put my men to ſtreighter allowance, <hi>viz.</hi> ſix men to a piece of Beef a day, and a pint of Peaſe for four men. And to prevent all diſcontent and murmuring, I kept my ſelf, as I had done all along, upon the level with them; giving them leave to take the firſt piece in choice, and I the ſecond for my own Meſs. Withal, I encouraged them daily to get what proviſion of ſuſtenance they could
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:50975:44"/> from ſhore: having finiſhed our Dragg, and fixed two Nets for catching Sea Eggs, of which we got this day three Buſhels. Theſe were the means of tempering, as well as ſparing our Salt-fleſh, which we ſhould have more need of at Sea, where we ſhould be bereaved of the helps this Harbour af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded us. Alas! Had we had but ſtore of proper and cheriſhing food, our ſufferings from the cold would have been eaſily born, by ſo many hardy and luſty men as I had then on board, with the plenty of firing we met with. Nay, had I been ſo lucky as to have brought, what I uſually did in former Voyages, quantities of <hi>Ruſſia</hi> Hams and Neats-Tongues, they would have af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded great ſupport under ſuch woful di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes. But to heighten the misfortune, I was baſely diſappointed at my coming a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, of a thouſand weight of Stock-fiſh, which I had agreed for, to take with me as Ship-proviſion. Strong <hi>Ruſſia</hi>-Beer too, (not to mention High Wines and Brandy) had been comfortable drinks in cold days; as I found by that little I had in Bottles, which I kept buried up in Straw, and preſerved moſtly from the froſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by; howbeit now and then the Boy fetch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Bottle, would bring the neck in one
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:50975:44"/> hand, and the bottom in the other, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut ſpilling any: perhaps one of the upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſt, and not well cover'd. And I cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orget, what I have more than once taken <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>otice of, that a Bottle of Beer ſtanding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ind us, while we ſat before the Fire, would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ontract Ice in the time we were drinking <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>The 8th, <hi>Tueſday.</hi> The weather was fair <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd ſomething warmer, the Wind being at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he S. W. I got my Sheat-Anchor and beſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ower on board, and made all clear for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a: Riding only by our ſmall Bower, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne Cable aſhore. In the Evening our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en dragged, and uſed their Nets, getting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me Scallops and 2 Buſhels of Eggs; to our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reat Relief. This day we firſt pumped the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hip, having in her about nine Inches of Water; neither had we occaſion to do it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rward: which was a happineſs, by reaſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e could not have kept our Pumps clear, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ithout a good ſupply of hot water; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>des the doing it often would have fatigued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur Men.</p>
            <p>The 9th, <hi>Wedneſday.</hi> In the morning it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ew a ſtout of Wind, at W. by N. with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow; but at noon the Wind was at W. S.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:50975:45"/> W. with Squauls of Snow. We got a Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Wood and Water; and carryed a Sha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Lines with 20 Hooks, out into the F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and left them all night, to ſee if we co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> take any Fiſh therewith.</p>
            <p>The 10th, <hi>Thurſday.</hi> We had fair we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther in the morning, and little Wind; ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> fetched on board our Lines, with the Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> entire, and no Fiſh. Before noon it blew <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtorm out of the Weſt, with abundance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Snow, which obliged me to let go my b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Bower under Foot: It continued to blo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> till midnight, and then the Wind eaſed.</p>
            <p>The 11th, <hi>Friday.</hi> In the morning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> was fair, and the Wind Southerly: Towar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> noon it fell a Snowing, and blew very ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at S. S. W. in the evening it froze ſmart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with abatement of Wind; inducing me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> heave up my beſt Bow-Anchor again; b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a great Snow followed, and bad weather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> night.</p>
            <p>The 12th, <hi>Saturday.</hi> It continued blo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing very hard at Weſt, with much Sno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in Squauls; ſo I was forc't to let drop <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Sheat-Anchor under foot. We had tw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:50975:45"/> Cats on board, whoſe lives we endeavoured <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> preſerve by giving them freſh Meat of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a Eggs and Muſcles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but they grew <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaker as the cold continued, and died of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e cold, ſtarved; one now, and the other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> week after, even at our feet, and before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Fire.</p>
            <p>The 13th, <hi>Sunday.</hi> It continued blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g very hard, the Wind at W N. W. and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. W. with much Snow, and violent Guſts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Wind.</p>
            <p>The 14th, <hi>Monday.</hi> We had not ſo much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ind on this, as the laſt 2 days, yet 'twas far <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ough from being Calm. I heaved up my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eat-Anchor and brought it on Board; got a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at load of Wood, and another of Water.</p>
            <p>The 15th, <hi>Tueſday.</hi> The good weather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the morning, invited our men aſhore to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther Periwinkles and Dills; but by 10 a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ock it began to blow a ſtorm at N. W. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> W. ſo that they could ſcarce get aboard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in. At three in the Afternoon, one of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t men departed this Life. He was under 30 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs of age, and taken firſt ſick at <hi>Archangel,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a diſtemper like an Ague, continuing ill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r ſince we came away from thence, and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:50975:46"/> declining till this time. Neither can it b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſaid he died of the cold meerly, ſuch as d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo (as I have been told) going off Sleeping <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> whereas he expired gradually and ſenſibly as I have ſeen others breathing their laſt could we have got home in good time, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> might poſſibly have recovered. The cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nuance of the Storm, made us let fall ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> beſt Bow-Anchor.</p>
            <p>The 16th, <hi>Wedneſday.</hi> The morning w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fair; ſo we heaved up our Sheat-Ancho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and buried our deceaſed Man at low wate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mark. For higher up on the dry ſhore, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Ground was ſo hard frozen, that we coul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not dig it. We got a Boat of Wood an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Water, and put the Dead mans Cloaths <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Sale at the Maſt; as our Cuſtom is at Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the like caſe. In the Evening the Win<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> came to the South, blowing and freezin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> extraordinary hard, with Squauls of Sno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Afterwards it ſhifted to N. N. E. continuit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtormy all night.</p>
            <p>The 17th, <hi>Thurſday.</hi> It grew Calm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> towards the morning, but it Snowed muc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and froze very hard all day; the Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> continuing at N. N. Eaſt till midnight, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> then came to the Weſt; and in the morni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> following to N. N. W.</p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:50975:46"/>
            <p>The 18th, <hi>Friday.</hi> The weather mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate enough as to Wind, but Snowing and Freezing ſo prodigiouſly, that our men who went aſhore to get Periwinkles and Dills, were forced aboard in a ſhort time, being not able to endure the weather abroad: and ſome of them were ſo benummed with the Cold, as to be uncapable of helping themſelves to climb the Ships ſide; ſo that others were forced to help, or hand them up. But ſoon after they got aboard, they recovered; the Ship being hot like a Stove, compared with the open Air. I remember for ſeveral days I could not bear the ſharpneſs of the Air, walking upon the Dcck, but was glad to clap my Handkerchief, double over my Mouth and Noſe, for a defence. You muſt know that for theſe four Months paſt, ſince we came in here, we ſuffered our Beards to grow at length for warmneſs; which would be often full of Icycles, from our Breath congealed, after the expoſing our ſelves for a little while upon Deck: but approaching the fire they came off eaſily, whereas to have pulled them before, had been to bring hair and all.</p>
            <p>The 19th, <hi>Saturday.</hi> We had little Wind this day, and that at N. W. but much Snow,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:50975:47"/> and Froſt ſo exceſſive, that it was impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for a man to look to Windward. In the mornings, after ſuch bitter nights as we had at this time, the Glaſs Windows of my Round-houſe where I lay, would have Ice upon them, of the thickneſs of a Crown piece; ſo that we were forced to ſcrape it off with a Knife to let in the Light. The great Cabbin Windows we kept ſhut up, with boards nailed without; as well for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of them againſt weather, as warmth, for the ten men I lodged there con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly. The Round-houſe I reſerved to my ſelf, though much colder; but I kept that in regard to the Proviſion I had ſtowed therein. And to make known to them, that I had ſhared the ſufferings with 'em, I ſhew'd them my Bed, which was frozem to the Boards on each ſide, that I durſt not allow the Boy to ſtir it, for fear of Tearing, thus for 5 months I left it, and went to it morning and night, not pulling off my Cloaths, ſave for ſhift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; only putting on my Furr-Gown at my ariſing, and plucking it off when I laid down, to throw over me, together with the Rugs and Blankets. And long ſince, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Inconveniency of going from the Fire in the Steerage, where I reſided by day, to my Lodging at Night, by reaſon of the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:50975:47"/> Snow, that laid upon the Quarter Deck, I ordered the Carpenter to Caulk up the Round-houſe door; ſo I made my paſſage by a Scuttle or Sally Port down into the great Cabbin, and by that means obſerved the order they kept below me. As I lay in my Bed, I could diſtinguiſh and tell every Nail in the Ceiling or elſewhere, either head or point, having a piece of Ice like E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namel upon it. I ſuppoſe from my moiſt breath condenſed and froze. My Books too that ſtood upon a ſhelf over my Head, had upon their edges and corners the ſame orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; a ſight I cannot ſay, whether more pleaſant or diſmal.</p>
            <p>The 20th, <hi>Sunday.</hi> 'Twas Calm, with much Snow falling, and continued Froſt; notwithſtanding I got up our Fore-yard and Mizen-yard in the Evening, in hopes of an Eaſt Wind: but by night, it came to Weſt, continuing fair.</p>
            <p>The 21ſt, <hi>Monday.</hi> This morning was calm and fair, after a ſerene and ſharp freez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing night; ſo that we could not but obſerve the ſurface of the water in the Bay about us, to be covered with a hard Scum or thin Ice; which made us fear being lockt up: But
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:50975:48"/> immediately the Wind ariſing at Weſt broke it all away. We got a Hogſhead of Water, and knockt off the Ice round the Ship, at the edge of the Water; and in the Evening our men went aſhore, for recruiting their freſh Proviſion: and towards night it blew ſo hard, that I was forced to lower our yards down again.</p>
            <p>The 22d, <hi>Tueſday.</hi> The day began with good weather enough as to Wind, only we had ſome Squauls of Snow; it froze too, but very moderately. We got a Boat of Wood; and our men going up the Hill a great height a Wooding, ſaw the Body of the Sun; reporting it when they came aboard with great Joy. And indeed it was a ſight for them to rejoyce at, having never ſeen it ſince they came into this Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. For it muſt be conſidered, we lay low in the Water, that we had leſs Light for that reaſon; yet was the want of that compenſated, by a more benign Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature of the Air as to cold, than we ſhould have found upon any part of the ſhore. For I am perſwaded, that no Houſe we might have made there, could with the ſame manner of warming it, that we made uſe of in the Ship, have preſerved us ſo well. Beſides a coldneſs perhaps from the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:50975:48"/> Earth it ſelf; I am ſure a ſmall height in the Atmoſphere, makes a ſenſible Variation as to heat and cold in the ſame place: Not to offer at any Reaſon, but our men found it ſo by daily experience, when they made but ſmall aſcents in Wooding and Watering. And the Mountains, or greater Hills which lay about us, being, as near as I could gueſs, above three hundred Fathom higher than the ſurface of the water in the Bay, ſeemed to have endured the utmoſt force of the Froſt; having Crowns or Caps of Ice; three or four Fathom thick in ſome places, and over-hanging like a Pent-houſe or Precipice, with a horrid proſpect at diſtance.</p>
            <p>We took 2 turns off the Hawſe, cleaned the Ships Deck of Snow and Ice, and clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Scuppers. At midnight it began to blow a ſtorm at S. W. but towards morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Wind came to the N. W. by W. the Storm continuing: ſo that I was forced to let fall my Sheat-Anchor.</p>
            <p>The 23d, <hi>Wedneſday.</hi> The Wind held hard at W. N. W. with much Snow; about 10 in the Forenoon, the Wind came to N. E. by N. continuing to Snow. At noon we heaved up our Sheat-Anchor, the Wind
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:50975:49"/> eaſing; but the evening it came more out of the Bay. This day, as I was walking upon the Deck, came a Fox upon a ſmall Hill over againſt the Ship, and ſtood a while looking upon us; but ſoon ran away, at a little noiſe we made.</p>
            <p>The 24th, <hi>Thurſday.</hi> We had the Wind at S. E. in the morning, with a gentle Gale, but freezing extraordinary hard: Howbeit we got a Boat of Water, and cleared our Decks from Snow and Ice. At noon the Sun ſhew'd itſelf upon our Maſts: I got my Fore-Top-Maſt up, with my Mizen-Yard and Fore-Yard; and towards night the Wind South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erd. I then made a ſtrict Survey of all our Proviſion, ſhifting it out of one Cask into another, that I might be certain how much there was; and found but 154 pieces of Beef on board. I gave to each of our men a pound and a quarter of Honey, for the uſe ſo often mentioned before. Some of them had been aſhore this afternoon, to get Dills and Periwinkles; but the weather was too cold to be endured, and they were forced to return aboard preſently.</p>
            <p>The 25th, <hi>Friday.</hi> By break of Day, the Wind being Eaſterly, I got all my Yards
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:50975:49"/> and Top-Maſts up, and the men went aſhore to caſt off the Cable; with a full Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for Sea: But before they could clear the Ice, and come to caſt it off, the Wind came to S. W. and W. S. W. beginning to blow and Snow. Before night I was forced to ſtrike both my Top-Maſts, and lower all down again ſnug: and at 10 the Storm was ſo furious, that our Men were contented to to abide here, notwithſtanding their late earneſtneſs to be going, acknowledging it a mercy from heaven to be detained.</p>
            <p>The 26th, <hi>Saturday.</hi> The Wind was grown moderate by the Morning, and at noon 'twas quite Calm; we took two turns off our Hawſe: and in the afternoon got a Boat load of Wood: the Skiff too went a dragging, geting but 15 Scallops. This mild Day gave us opportunity to obſerve, that the Sluces or Drains of Water, that fell into the Bay, were ſo conſiderable, as to make a ſmall motion toward the Sea at low Water.</p>
            <p>It is to be noted, we had no River run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning into this Harbour, or any which we call back-waters, but the fore-mentioned drains; all of them not being ſufficient to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:50975:50"/> ſupply a Current. It flowed South Weſt a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a full and New Moon, riſing and falling a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Nep-Tides about eight foot, and at Spring<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Tides about twelve or fourteen. How i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was in the <hi>Fuel,</hi> we can give no poſitiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> account, but by my obſervation, upon ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> points the Tide did ſeem to move indiffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rently ſtrong; for when I was out with the Boat, I perceived ſome Riplings; and our men in ſearching, fell in with pretty ſtrong Tides, but could not inform me di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly. Above all things I well remember, the old <hi>Finniſh</hi> People, when they came aboard our Ship, told me there was never a Rock or dangerous Shoal in the whole <hi>Fuel.</hi> And I have taken care to have the Depth of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and anchoring places marked in the Char<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> faithfully, according to the ſeveral Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries made by me and my Mate, and the diſtances of places computed with the beſt of my Judgment: To which I refer the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Towards night the Wlnd Souther'd, blowing and freezing hard.</p>
            <p>The 27th, <hi>Sunday.</hi> We had a ſmall Snow falling all day, but ſo very mild withal, that it melted as it fell, and that likewiſe that which laid before upon the Ship; and toward night it turned to rain wrth the Wind at S. W.</p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:50975:50"/>
            <p>The 28th, <hi>Monday.</hi> The morning was Stormy, the Wind at Weſt, ſo that I was neceſſitated to let go my Sheat-Anchor; but toward noon the Wind eaſed, and I heaved it up again. I called all my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany together, and told them, that the time had ſpent ſo much of our Proviſion, that we could not venture to Sea, with what we had remaining, where we ſhould be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaved of all the little comforts and helps we had from the Shore. And therefore while we had any thing left, we muſt go and make ſearch for people, whereby to get Proviſion, to carry us out of this place, and to our much deſired homes.</p>
            <p>That ſince Almighty God had wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully preſerved us till this time, when the weather was grown more moderate, and the days of a brave length; we ought not only to expreſs our Thanks in words, to that Being of all Goodneſs, for our preſervation paſt, but to be active and induſtrious for the future, ſhewing our ſelves thereby more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Creatures.</p>
            <p>And finding ſuch diſcourſe to have ſome effect upon them, I ordered the Long-Boat to be immediately hoiſed in and Cawked,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:50975:51"/> and other things done, that might be for the ſafety and conveniency of the men in her. It proved a fair day and thawed, whereby we got one ſide Graved in a few hours, fitted her Sails, and put many things in readineſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>March</hi> the 1ſt, <hi>Tueſday.</hi> The month and day began with fair weather; and after we had made an end of trimming the Long-Boat and got her out, we went all hands aſhore, to get what we could for the Belly: and towards night got our Yards and Top-Maſts up, reſolving to keep in a moving po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture.</p>
            <p>The 2d, <hi>Wedneſday.</hi> It began to blow hard at W. S. W. and ſo came to S. a violent Storm; inſomuch, that we were forced to ſtrike both Yards and Top-Maſt down again: but towards night the Wind eaſed, and it froze at an exceſſive rate. This day the Sun ſhined on board the Ship over the Hills; it being the firſt time of my ſeeing the ſame ſince I came in here, being 17 weeks. Note, that though the Sun at this time did not remain above the Horizon, quite ſo long as it does in <hi>England,</hi> and its <hi>Meridian</hi> Altitude but little, yet their day was even as long, conſidering the more
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:50975:51"/> early day-break, and the more laſting twilight in the evening. And who knows not, that upon the 10th of this Month, the days and nights are equal all the World over?</p>
            <p>The 3d, <hi>Thurſday.</hi> It proved a very fair day, with much Sun-ſhine and little Wind; we had not ſeen the like before in this place. This put ſuch Life in our Men, that they got up our Top-Maſts at once, and looſed the Sails for drying them; they having con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſtill folded up now for ſome time; and according to our expectation they were found well: here being no fear of their get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting heat to rot them. In the afternoon our Men went aſhore to get Dills and Periwin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles, ſome dragged in the Long-Boat and got Scallops, and others in the Skiff with their Nets, made good purchaſe of Sea Eggs. When night came on, I could not but obſerve our people as buſy, as they are uſually in a Cooks Shop about the <hi>Exchange</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> between the Hours of Twelve and Two: only with this difference, that every man was there both Gueſt and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant. This with a Kettle, that a Sauce-pan, and the other a Diſh or Platter; ſome dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings Dills, ſome Scallops, Muſcles, and Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winkles, and others boiling Sea-eggs in
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:50975:52"/> Broath; and ſome were brewing of Mead: ſo that at both Hearths, there were ſcarce room enough for one to get in between to light a Pipe. I can't ſay of Tobacco, for there was none but what I had; what the men ſmoak'd for ſuch, they took as much pains to prepare, as to Cook a diſh of Meat.</p>
            <p>The 4th, <hi>Friday.</hi> In the morning the Wind was at Weſt South Weſt, a ſtrong Gale, with clear weather, but at Noon it ſnowed: However, we got a Boat load of Wood. Toward night fell little Wind, and that at North North Weſt.</p>
            <p>The 5th, <hi>Saturday.</hi> It proved a hard ſtorm Southerly, ſo that I was forced to ſtrike our Yards and Top-Maſts, and let fall our Sheat-Anchor; it freezing very hard all day, with clear Weather over head.</p>
            <p>The 6th, <hi>Sunday.</hi> We heaved up our Sheat-Anchor again, the day beginning with little Wind, and continued handſome Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther till eight at night, when the Wind came to South South Weſt, and it fell a Snowing.</p>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:50975:52"/>
            <p>The 7th, <hi>Monday.</hi> It blew hard in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orning at W. S. Weſt, and a great Sea <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me tumbling in, which obliged us to let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll our Anchor again. At noon it abated, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd came more Weſterly; at 8 at night we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd a Storm at N. N. Weſt, but blowing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y and indifferent warm.</p>
            <p>The 8th, <hi>Tueſday.</hi> The day broke with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tle Wind, but that running from E. to S. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d S. W. and to W. S. W, and then a freſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le, but dry and warm. We got a load of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ood, and filled a Cask of Mead, for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en that were to go in the Boat. At this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne I found all of our men complaining of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ins in their Bones, which my Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on did conclude, were the effects of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſt in their Limbs; generally remarkable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on the abatement of the weather: which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> found true, obſerving upon the return of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tream Froſt, we were without Ailment, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> upon a Thaw, we felt the ſame pains <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in. The like indiſpoſition I experienced my ſelf, at ſuch times.</p>
            <p>The 9th, <hi>Wedneſday.</hi> The fairneſs and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mneſs of the weather gave us opportunity getting two turns off our Hawſe, heaving our Sheat-Anchor, drying our Top-Sails,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:50975:53"/> and fetching three Hogſheads of Wate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> We likewiſe fixed a Fire-hearth in our Lon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Boat, which we made two days before, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fitted a Sail to ſpread over the ſame, if the ſhould be forced to lye in her; and got a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> things ready to ſet her forth at half a hours warning. The Wind came to S. Weſt, the Sky looking Squauly, but prove very fair.</p>
            <p>The 10th, <hi>Thurſday.</hi> We had goe weather in the Morning, and a Souther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Wind; I cauſed all my Men but four, (wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were ſick or unſound,) to caſt Lots wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhould go in the Boat, and they fell to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as able as I could have picked out: Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> beit, two of them bought it off with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> others, for ten Shillings each, to be pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them, when they ſhould receive their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpective wages, at the end of the Voyag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> My Mates drew by themſelves, and the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fell to my Second Mate; a man fit enoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for the buſineſs. I immediately ſent the away with Money, Linnen-Cloath, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> other things, which I judged might be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for Traffick with the Inhabitants, if th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhould find any.</p>
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:50975:53"/>
            <p>Towards Noon the Wind came Weſterly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith much Snow, withal Freezing hard, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t handſome weather of Wind: and at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ght at night it came to the N. N. Weſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d brought back our Boat again, having <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ade little diſcovery.</p>
            <p>The 11th, <hi>Friday.</hi> The Wind was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>utherly, and the Morning fair; ſo I ſent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Long-Boat away again on her former <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rand. With thoſe I had on board, I got Skiff of Wood; I mean the ſoundeſt of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>em, for the reſt had the Froſt in their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et or Hands. The Wind continued in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne Quarter all the Afternoon, but at night <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>w very hard.</p>
            <p>The 12th, <hi>Saturday.</hi> It blew hard at S. E. and froze ſharply all day.</p>
            <p>The 13th, <hi>Sunday.</hi> It blew freſh at S. by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt all day, but dry over Head, with a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d Froſt.</p>
            <p>The 14th, <hi>Monday.</hi> The weather was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry uncertain, ſometimes Squauly, now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h Wind and then fair and clear. While was ſo, all that were on board and able,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:50975:54"/> went aſhore, gathering Dills and Periwin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles, and ſuch as they could get for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Belly.</p>
            <p>The 15th, <hi>Tueſday.</hi> In the morning i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>proved fair and clear, ſo that ſome of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Folks went aſhore to ſeek for Proviſion, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> others continued in the Skiff, dragging fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Shell-fiſh. Thoſe upon Land happene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to eſpy two Boats coming into the Bay, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> rowing towards the Ship. They preſent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> imagined 'em to be ſome of their Com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pany ſent out 4 days before, and fell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Hollowing to their Fellows in the Skiff which ſo affrighted the people in the Boat that they immediately turned about an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> made away. And though I called to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Skiff with all ſpeed to come aboard, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſent a man to the point to ſee for the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> yet ſuch haſte they made, as to be out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſight before he came. Soon after ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them appeared upon the point, and cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nued looking upon the Ship a good whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> In the mean time I ſent a man up one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Hills, to diſcover which way th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> went, but he returned without being ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to give any Account of them. So we loſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> opportunity of Commerce with them, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> then if they had not been unluckily ſca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:50975:54"/> by noiſe, would doubtleſs have come on board us of their own accord: for the Ship lay, in a manner, between them and our men in the Skiff and aſhore; and I gueſſed they were wholly taken up with the ſight of the Ship, where by my order we lay ſilent and hid: and for the future I commanded every one to be ſo, upon the like occaſion. Theſe people, we ſuppoſe, were coming to take their Summer Habitation, in the Houſes we deſcribed before: for to me it ſeemed, as if there were Cattle and Children in the Boat, but I could not, by all the Enquiry I made, of thoſe whom I ſaw afterwards, learn who they were, or whether I gueſt aright of their intentions. In the Afternoon it blew freſh at S. S. E. However we filled 3 Hog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheads of water.</p>
            <p>The 16th, <hi>Wedneſday.</hi> All the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon was calm and fair, which our men ſpent, in dragging for Scallops and Sea-Eggs, and gathering Dills and Periwinkles, at low Water.</p>
            <p>At noon I took Boat and rowed out to a Hill, lying at the Mouth of the Harbour, and went up it as high as I durſt venture, to look about the <hi>Fuel.</hi> And S. of us I
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:50975:55"/> thought I ſaw ſeveral Iſlands, but could not diſcern the bottom of the <hi>Fuel,</hi> which ran in very far and wide.</p>
            <p>The 17th, <hi>Thurſday.</hi> It continued fair, and our Men went aſhore a Wooding, but had not been gone above two hours before they diſcovered a Yaul coming towards the Ship; and according to the order given be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, we let 'em come aboard us very ſilently, expecting it was one of the Boats we ſaw two days before. But it proved to be a Yaul that came from the North Cape, with four of our own men in her, and one <hi>Finlander;</hi> ſent by my Mate to ſatisfie me, how things ſtood there with the Long-Boat. And indeed it was high time to releaſe me from the fears I was in about them. He ſent in her a Barrel of Beef, a Barrel of Rye-Meal, 40 pound of Oatmeal, 80 pound of Stock-fiſh, with other Proviſions of Fleſh, <hi>viz.</hi> Mutton, Pork, and Veniſon, all dryed; and a ſmall Cask of Beer. They likewiſe brought us the news of a Peace concluded between <hi>England,</hi> the reſt of the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, and <hi>France:</hi> and gave me the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing account of what hapened to them, from the time of their departure. <q rend="margQuotes">After we had ſailed to the other ſide of the <hi>Fuel,</hi>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:50975:55"/> we got ſight of a little Yaul, and gave her chace, having the Wind of her, and it blowing freſh. They made for the ſhore, and juſt as they landed we fell in with them. There were but three men in the Boat, who got out and run for it upon the Snow, two of which our men could in no wiſe overtake, but the other they caught: He was an old man, and they were his Sons. Our Crew treated him civilly, and having two <hi>Daniſh</hi> men born, in the Company, they fell to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe him, and ſoon ſettled a right under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding between one another; that he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately called the young men, that ſtood a loof off to ſee what would become of their Father. They readily obeyed, and parlying with them altogether, our men offered them two Dollars, if they would conduct us to a Prieſts Houſe, or ſome Town, where we might get Proviſion for Money or Goods. So they came to an agreement; the old man and one of his Sons forthwith ſtepping into our Boat. But we having a brisk Gale, in towing the Yaul after us, pulled her Stem in pieces, and ſo were forced to caſt her off; the old man bidding his Son that was in her, to go aſhore, and directed us to keep on our
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:50975:56"/> way. This we did till we came to the outermoſt point, where we went aſhore, finding there ſome Houſes, and about four Families; the Hamlet or Village being called by name of <hi>Swetwel.</hi> In this place we took up our Lodging all night, and the day following being ſtormy, we durſt not put to Sea. All this time we received kind entertainment from the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, and our Company likewiſe were as free of what they had to them. The day after being <hi>Sunday</hi> we parted from thence, and with all ſpeed made for the Town of <hi>Colwitch</hi> upon the Cape, where we arrived by two in the After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, the people being at Church. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Sermon they came all and made much of us, hearing our ſtory, and admired that we were able to live on Board, in ſo extraordinary hard Winter: for ſo it was accounted with them. They ſeemed very kind to us, till the Miniſter and the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant fell out, about ſelling our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion. For one ſaid it belonged to him, and the other as much; but between them both, we were furniſhed at their own rates, being glad to get it any way. It hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened at this time, there was one from the Governor of <hi>Ward-houſe,</hi> who came to
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:50975:56"/> look after the Salvage of a <hi>Dutch</hi> Fly-boat, that was loſt in the ſame Storm, that drove us in, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and from him they had the good news of the Peace.</q>
            </p>
            <p>That night I diſpatched away the ſame Boat again (which was a Yaul belonging to ſome of the Town, of whom our peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple had hired it for four Dollars) and ſent her to the ſame place upon the Cape, with more Goods and Money for purchaſing more Proviſion; with order for my own Long-Boat to return on Board, with all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient ſpeed. Yet as I underſtood after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, they were in great danger of being loſt; had not one of the Inhabitants coming along with them, and knowing the Coaſts well, happily directed them to a place of ſafety, during the Storm they met with.</p>
            <p>The 18th, <hi>Friday.</hi> In the morning it blew a Storm at S. S. E. but towards noon it abated, yet Snowing much till 5 in the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternon; becoming then fair and clear, with little Wind, and that ſhifting to W. S. W.</p>
            <p>The 19th, <hi>Saturday.</hi> We got a Boats loading of Wood, it continuing Calm, and
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:50975:57"/> fair till 5 in the Afternoon; from which time it Snowed till 8 at night: But all the while moderate as to Wind.</p>
            <p>The 20th, <hi>Sunday.</hi> In the morning came a Yaul from the Miniſters Houſe, that lived fifteen miles from us, towards the North Kyne; and in her a Clerk or Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary of the Governors, that reſides at <hi>Ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe.</hi> This perſon was the ſame that our Men before had told me of, who came now on purpoſe to ſee me, after he had croſſed over the <hi>Fuel,</hi> to make his return; his way being then all over Land, and that upon the Snow. He told me, that he boggled nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at Mountain or Valley, but could go in 14 hours time 16 <hi>Daniſh</hi> Miles, which make 64 of ours. And accordingly ſhewed me how he was fitted for ſuch a Journey, having with him a Leathern Canoa, in the faſhion of a Weavers Shuttle, only turned up more at the ends. This was carried in his Boat, when he went by Water, but at Land it ſerved as a Sledge does in <hi>Holland</hi> when the Rivers are frozen; having 3 Iron Keels at the bottom, and being drawn by a Rain Deer. It had a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering like a Deck, with a hole in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, coming cloſe about his waſte: So that
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:50975:57"/> with a Furr Coat over the upper part of his Body, and other Cloathing beneath, he was well provided againſt the worſt of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. In his hand he carried a Paddle, or ſmall Oar to keep him from overturning. In the way are no Inns, but he makes his nights Lodging at ſome Miniſters Houſe, where he ſtill finds free quarter.</p>
            <p>He informed me of two <hi>Dutch</hi> Ships that were forced into the Harbour of <hi>Ward-houſe,</hi> by the ſame Storm that forced me in, where I then lay: that he ſuppoſed they were now going to Sea; their men having laid on board in order thereto 3 days before he came from thence. I thought that might very well be, conſidering the great advantage they had of me, being at the principal Town of the whole Country, even where the Governor himſelf lived; where they could want for little, but had good <hi>Daniſh</hi> Houſes, with Stoves in them, to keep them warm. And one thing this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man told me, too conſiderable to omit; namely, That from <hi>Ward-houſe</hi> aforeſaid, there went a Poſt to <hi>Copenhagen</hi> every fort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night. So that if any Ship be forc't in there or thereabouts by ſtreſs of weather, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Miniſters Houſe, they may ſend to
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:50975:58"/> the Town, and from thence to any part of <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this Boat came the Miniſters Son, who brought both dry and new Fiſh, and pretty ſtore; with ſeveral preſents from his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as a Calf new killed, with Cheeſe and Milk for my Men: alſo dryed Mutton, and Hams of Bacon, Veniſon and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridge.</p>
            <p>The 21ſt, <hi>Monday.</hi> It blew freſh at S all day; notwithſtanding there came a <hi>Finniſh</hi> Boat on board me, and brought me ſtore of Fiſh and dryed Mutton, with a ſmall parcel of freſh Butter and Cheeſe. I bought all they had but ſome Veniſon and Partridge, which at their going away they preſented me with; I giving them in gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity ſuch as I had; <hi>viz.</hi> a few Raiſins, (a great rarity with them,) and ſome Mead. Their Veniſon was lean and horridly black, but the Partridges were dainty, being freſh killed and fat.</p>
            <p>The 22d, <hi>Tueſday.</hi> It proved a Storm; the Wind all Southerly, withal freezing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding hard; but dry over head.</p>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:50975:58"/>
            <p>The 23d, <hi>Wedneſday.</hi> It was ſo fair and calm, that we cleared our Hawſe. This day came another Boat on board, and brought us Fiſh of ſeveral kinds, both dry and wet, <hi>viz.</hi> Cod, Ling, and Turbut; ſome Butter and Cheeſe, with dry'd Fleſh of the ſorts aforeſaid. <hi>Note,</hi> that this Meat was not ſalted, but prepared thus for keeping, by being hung up in their Chimneys. It had little of goodneſs or nouriſhment, and ſcarce appeared to ſwell by boyling. But I took all they had, in truck for Cloath, and Cloaths made up; and ſome I bought with Money. The Boat they came in, was of the faſhion of a <hi>Norway</hi>-Yaul, big enough for ſix Rowers, and ſo many they had: but ſome others had but four, being leſs; and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe there were for two only. The people are low of ſtature, of Limbs well ſet, freſh colour'd in the Face, though of a dirty hue, and an ill ſmell attending them. But whether it is from their lying in their Cloaths, or their natural ſavour, perhaps derived from their conſtant Diet upon Fiſh, I could not determine with my ſelf. Their hair is generally light coloured and lank, cut like the <hi>Danes:</hi> They wear their Beards of a full growth, young and old: Their Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:50975:59"/> too is like the <hi>Norwegians, viz.</hi> Cloſe Breeches, ſhort Coats, both made of courſe Cloath, with Caps of the ſame furred. Their Shoes are pulled up half way on their Legs like Boots, with Toes turning up like the tip of a Half Moon painted, and furred within. One thing peculiar in this peoples Garb I obſerved, and that was, they every one carried a ſmall Powder-Horn, hanging under their Chins, by a ſtring about their Necks. For what uſe or purpoſe I could not learn, tho I asked them as well as I could, but could not explain their Anſwers; for my <hi>Dane</hi> that remained on board, was then as I thought, almoſt at the point of death; that is, ſo weak, as not to do the work of an Interpreter. The Governour's man too, could not ſpeak <hi>Dutch</hi> enough to be intelligible to me, when I enquired into the ſame thing three days before, though I underſtood he was a <hi>German</hi> born.</p>
            <p>The 24th, <hi>Thurſday.</hi> It proved fair, the Wind at South Weſt; we got a Boat of Wood. Toward night it weſter'd, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 8 our Long-Boat returned on board, and brought with them a Barrel of Beef, a Barrel of Rye-Meal, and 3 hundred weight
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:50975:59"/> of Stock-fiſh, with other Proviſions which we wanted; namely, ſome dry'd Mutton and Pork, and ſome Bread alſo, with But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Cheeſe, to our great comfort; we being therewith ſufficiently ſtored for the Sea. And from them I took this following re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation; That the Town of <hi>Colwitch</hi> and the Cape conſiſted of about 14 Houſes, with as many Families, and one Church. The Houſes are built after the <hi>Norway</hi> faſhion, of Wood, with Stoves placed in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, or ſo as to warm the Rooms, without the ſight of Fire; they being a kind of Ovens, and are heated after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. Their Houſes have Windows of Glaſs, but with Wooden Shutters, both in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and outward, which they make cloſe in the Winter, by ſtopping or caulking them with Moſs. So they keep up ſeveral weeks, in the dark and cold ſeaſon, burning great Tallow Candles continually; ſome of which our men ſaw. The Church was of the ſame materials with their Houſes, being one Room, able to contain about thirty perſons. Four or five of theſe Churches or Chappels are ſerved by one Teacher about three times in the year; (for it is to be ſuppoſed they only Congregate in the Summer.) They are uſually placed
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:50975:60"/> about five or ſix miles off each other, or nearer, according as the Country is more or leſs populous. But one Paſtor lives ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally fifteen miles from another, who is maintained by every tenth Fiſh; and where he reſides not, he empowers one to gather the Tithe as they take them. By this means they are furniſhed with Merchandize, which they ſell, or exchange for other things they want, with Ships that come yearly to their Port Town to fetch them, and bring goods accordingly. Hence they come to be the moſt wealthy and conſiderable of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. They are Lawyers, Juſtices of the Peace, and cuſtomarily ſole in Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. For their Education is the moſt liberal, being, as I was informed, in a School, or petty Univerſity in <hi>Norway,</hi> near <hi>Dronthem.</hi> They too obſerve the greateſt Hoſpitality; all Travellers being entertained by them, and furniſhed with Sleds or Rain-Deer, from one to another: the like alſo was I told by the Governour's Man before, when he informed me, of their way of Travelling. They breed Cattle of a ſmall kind, with Goats and Sheep; and Swine alſo. The former are fed in the Summer with Graſs, of which they have plenty at that time; but in the Winter they gather Rock-weeds
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:50975:60"/> at low Water, and Boyl them in Coppers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ade for the purpoſe, to take the Salt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t; and then give them to their Beaſts to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t. They have Horſes too of very mean <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ature, who have the ſame food: But the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ogs I gueſs are nouriſhed by Fiſh, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the dryed Pork they brought me, had a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rong taſte of it. Their Cuſtoms and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers are much like thoſe of the <hi>Danes,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er whoſe Dominion they are; and every <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an from fifteen to ſixty, is Taxed at two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ollars each, which they pay yearly, either Fiſh or Money, to the King of <hi>Denmark</hi>'s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ollectors: and for that, they have a ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>g Protection, and a Liberty of living <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here they pleaſe; which in Summer is up <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d down the Country; but in Winter they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tire to their Joint Habitations fitted up <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itably. Their Religion too is <hi>Daniſh,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>g of the Reformed Lutheran Church, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elief and diſcipline; their Sermons being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eached, and their Divine Services per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rmed in the ſame Language. So that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ough they have another Language Antient <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d Native in the Country, yet they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>and and uſe the <hi>Daniſh</hi> moſtly. As to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eir Women I can ſay but little, not ſeeing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y my ſelf, nor did the Men, I ſent pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nd to give any account of their Behaviour,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:50975:61"/> or how they managed their Families. The only told me, that their habit was like th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Daniſh</hi> Womens; but I could not but b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lieve the better ſort of them love fine Cloath as well as our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Dames. For ſendin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a piece of wrought Silk of 7 or 8 Yard the Miniſters Wife at the Cape bought readily: and to ſhew how much ſhe w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pleaſed with her bargain, over and abov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the price ſhe agreed to and paid, ſhe ſent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a dozen of Partridges, and a Cheeſe. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Husband too, made me a preſent of a ſma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Cask of Beer. Nor was the Mercha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> behind him in Civility, ſending me a fre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Leg of Beef, but killed a Month befor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and without any Salt preſerved by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Froſt: and ſome dry Mutton withal. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> truley they might well enough afford i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conſidering how dearly I paid for my Prov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>The 25th, <hi>Friday.</hi> It held fair, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> little Wind at S. S. E. betimes in the Mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing I called all hands up, and heaved <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> our Sheat-Anchor, which we carried o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> before the Long-Boat went away, and g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our Yards and Top-Maſts up, clearing o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Decks and Skuppers from Snow and Ice, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> making that night all fit for the Sea; havin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:50975:61"/> longing expectation, and great hopes it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght be on the morrow.</p>
            <p>The 26th, <hi>Saturday.</hi> There was but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Wind ſtirring this Morning, all we had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s from the South Eaſt, notwithſtanding get out, we unmoored, and got a peek our ſmall Bower, and our Cable aboard, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ving only a Towling aſhore to caſt the Ship. that time our Men had got their Breakfaſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich was a high word with us then, and began to ſpeak it chearfully) it proved <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>air Gale at S. W. we heaved up our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or, and caſt off our Hawſe, and got out the <hi>Fuel,</hi> where we found the Wind fair <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i Southerly: But eſpying a Boat rowing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ards us, we laid to, and took her up. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it was the ſame perſon that came before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th the Governours Man, <hi>viz.</hi> the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Son, a young man about 30 years of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e. By him his Father ſent me tokens <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hly acceptable, that is to ſay, a whole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f ready roaſted, a rarity, but not a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, becauſe entire; ſeeing it was not much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ger than one of our Hares, ready dreſt <hi>England.</hi> Alſo a Runlet of Beer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with Kid or Wooden Veſſel of Milk, contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> above three Gallons; which was very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eet and good. A ſmall quantity of Curds
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:50975:62"/> too, freſh and tender; with a couple o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> little thick Cheeſes, well taſted, but a litt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtrong of the Runnet: over and above, Ham of their choice Bacon. I had mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ado to force a preſent upon him, his Fath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> having charged him, not to take any thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of me, that I ſhould want in my paſſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> home. At length I perſwaded him to carry h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Mother a Pound of white Sugar, and a Pot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Honey, and a parcel of Raiſins, and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſented himſelf with two Silk Hankerchie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo we parted, he for his home, and I ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the beſt of my way for Sea.</p>
            <p>We ſailed in the middle of the <hi>Fuel</hi> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſafety, ſo that we could make no nice obſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vation of the Land; beſides we were mig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tily diſabled for diſtant Views, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſmoke of our Green-wood Fires, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> had endured ſo long. Howbeit we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> cerned the ſhore to lye high on either ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with Wood upon it in ſome places; but none ſo much as where we lay: as we h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> been told before by the people of the Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>try. So that we happened well into place, ſo plentifully ſupplied with what could not have lived without.</p>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:50975:62"/>
            <p>At four in the Afternoon we got out of the <hi>Fuel;</hi> by eight at night we were length of the Eaſtermoſt part of the Cape. It blew hard at S. S. Weſt, ſo that I was forced to both my Sails.</p>
            <p>The 27th, <hi>Sunday.</hi> The Wind ſhifted from S. W. to Weſt, blowing ſo hard, as to put me by both my Top-ſails. At twelve at noon, we reckoned the North Cape to bear S. E. half Eaſt, diſtant 42 Miles. I made my way this 24 hours N. W. half Weſt; diſtance 49 miles.</p>
            <p>The 28th, <hi>Monday.</hi> By 10. at night the Wind eaſed, and we ſet our Main-Top-Sail; at two in the morning we ſet our Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Top-Sail, it being handſome weather: at ſix in the Morning, we ſet our Main-Stay-Sail and Mizen-Stay-Sail. All this time the Wind continued ſhifting between S. W. by S. and Weſt. I made my way N. W. 3d. Weſt: diſtance 47 miles</p>
            <p>The 29th, <hi>Tueſday.</hi> We had moderate weather as to Wind, and that ſhifting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween South, and S. W. by Weſt. I made my way this 24 hours N. N. W. diſtance 47 miles. It being almoſt ſtark Calm between times.</p>
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:50975:63"/>
            <p>The 30th, <hi>Wedneſday.</hi> It blew a Stou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Wind till 5 in the morning, when i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> began to abate, and fell a Snowing, and freezing very hard withal: I tacked to the Southward. By twelve at noon it grew Calm. I made my way this 24 hours W. by N. half Northerly: diſtance 68 Miles This day I got an obſervation, and foun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> my ſelf to be in the latitude of 73 degrees, and 25 minutes.</p>
            <p>The 31ſt, <hi>Thurſday.</hi> It proved very fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> weather, but very cold, the Wind holding between the S. by Weſt and S. E. with a moderate Gale; and towards Noon we had it mighty Calm, with a ſmooth Sea. I made my way S. W. half Weſt: diſtance 67 Miles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>April</hi> the 1ſt, <hi>Friday.</hi> It blew hard, the Wind ſhifting between the S. S. E. and Weſt; the Sea going very high. I made my way W. S. W. 3 d. Weſt: diſtance 57 Miles.</p>
            <p>The 2d, <hi>Saturday.</hi> It continued to blow as the day before, Snowing at an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive rate, and froze ſo exceeding hard,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:50975:63"/> that all the water that flew into the Ship, became Ice in a ſmall time. Inſomuch, that the Ship it ſelf, both within and without, was compleatly lined and covered with Ice: and nothing about us was fit to be handled. The Wind came to the North; ſo we made ſhift to get our Main-Sail hauled up, and bound together, as well as we could, and ſtood away with our Fore-Sail; it look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dreadfully a-ſtern of us. But toward noon the face of things was altered, and I got another Obſervation, finding my ſelf thereby in the Latitude of 71 degrees and 46 minutes.</p>
            <p>Then we ſet our Main-Sail again, but there was no ſpreading it, it was ſo hard frozen; and to pull it down we were forced to bring the Tackle to our Tacks and Sheats, ſtraining them as hard as we durſt, for fear of pulling the Sail in pieces: after all, we could not get it above half ſpread. We ſet our Sprit-Sail too, but all the Watch, which were ten Men, were two hours in getting it looſe. In the afternoon I went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſetting my Fore-Top-Sail; but could not get it out of the Top, by all the ways we could deviſe. I made my way S. W. 3 d. Weſt: diſtances 35 Miles.</p>
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:50975:64"/>
            <p>The 3d, <hi>Sunday.</hi> It was moderate e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough as to Wind, and that between the N. and Eaſt; but it froze exceſſively. This day with great toil and labour, I got both my Top-Sails ſet; looſing the Sails by degrees, and letting them dry; and bringing the Sheats to the Windles, with Looff-Tackles, I got them ſpread. I made my way S. W. by S. diſtance 73 miles.</p>
            <p>The 4th, <hi>Monday.</hi> We had mild wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this day, the Wind ſhifting round; and now and then it Snowed. I made my way W. S. W. 1 d. Weſt: diſtance 54 Miles.</p>
            <p>The 5th, <hi>Tueſday.</hi> The Wind came to to South, and ſo to Weſt, blowing hard, that we were forced to take in our Top-Sails, and at laſt our Fore-Sail. At ten in the forenoon we Reefed our Fore-Sail and Mizen, and tacked to the Southward, ſo that I made my way W. by N. diſtance but 34 Miles.</p>
            <p>The 6th, <hi>Wedneſday.</hi> Little Wind had we all this day, and that running round the Compaſs; but the Froſt fixt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere.
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:50975:64"/> The way I made was S. S. E. 1 d. Eaſt; diſtance but 19 miles.</p>
            <p>The 7th, <hi>Thurſday.</hi> Not much Wind to day, but ſhifting between the South and W. S. W. with cloſe weather. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding I made my way S. by Eaſt: diſtance 22 Miles.</p>
            <p>The 8th, <hi>Friday.</hi> The former part of the day it blew very hard, obliging us to hand both our Top-Sails; but in the after-part proved ſo moderate, that we ſet them again: the Wind ſhifting from S. to S. W. by S. we made our way Weſt, half Southerly: diſtance 63 Miles.</p>
            <p>The 9th, <hi>Saturday.</hi> It proved Squauly, but indifferent as to Wind. We handed our Fore-Top-Sail twice, and ſet him again as otf. The Wind ſhifting between S. and S. W. I held my courſe for 51 Miles Weſt, half Southerly.</p>
            <p>The 10th, <hi>Sunday.</hi> We met with hard Gales, firſt at South, and then coming to Weſt: which put us under a Main courſe. I held on my way S. W. 5 d. Southerly: di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance 65 Miles.</p>
            <pb n="106" facs="tcp:50975:65"/>
            <p>The 11th, <hi>Monday.</hi> It remained ſtormy weather, attended with abundance of Snow falling, and exceeding hard Froſt. I was forced to Reef my Main-Sail as well as we could, but in a ſorry manner, ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born as it was, and ſo much Snow lodged in it. The Wind was at S. E; ſo I made my way Weſt 42 Miles.</p>
            <p>The 12th, <hi>Tueſday.</hi> The Wind came to E. S. E. and ſo about to N. by W. with a great deal of Snow, and freezing extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary hard. I made my way good to the South 92 miles.</p>
            <p>The 13th, <hi>Wedneſday.</hi> Good weather enough as to Wind, but the Snow fell very thick. At Midnight it blew from the N. W. towards day from the E. and by S. little Wind. At break of day it fell quite Calm, freezing very hard. I made my way South; diſtance 94 miles.</p>
            <p>The 14th, <hi>Thurſday.</hi> The Wind came to N. E. and then to North W. blowing ſo very hard, that I could carry nothing, but a Fore-Courſe: we had a great Sea out of the South; but in the morning I ſet my Main-Sail again, after the beſt manner I
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:50975:65"/> could: ſo hard frozen was it, that I could not get it above half ſpread, though I lower'd my Main-Yard above 3 foot down. I made my way South: diſtance 117 Miles.</p>
            <p>The 15th, <hi>Friday.</hi> We had a Brave Wind from the W. and by N. which made us ſtrive hard to bring our Fore-Top-Sail to be ſerviceable, getting it off the top, and by meer ſtrength forced open ſome part of it; and ſo ſtood away with it for four hours: after which time it relented, enlarged and became more uſeful. By which means I made my way S. diſtance 123 Miles.</p>
            <p>The 16th, <hi>Saturday.</hi> It blew a ſtout of Wind at N. N. W. ſo that I had made my way S. by W; diſtance 142 Miles. By twelve at noon we ſaw <hi>Fowley Iſland,</hi> to the E. S. E. of us, diſtant eighteen Miles. We had brave moderate weather at this Time; and now we heard Rats about the Ship, who began to be Infenſe and Vexatious to us, in ſeizing upon our new Stock-fiſh. It is manifeſt they kept cloſe all the cold ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but our ſick Men who lay below with my Surgeon and Carpenter, (who was an old Man and kept conſtantly a Lamp burning
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:50975:66"/> by him,) never ſaw any of them, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived them in the leaſt to ſtir. How they lived ſo long on Board we gueſſed afterward, when we found they had eaten holes in our Maſts, and made themſelves places to lye in. And for drink they could get none, but by licking the Ice Casks; though no body ſaw ſuch a thing done by them.</p>
            <p>The 17th, <hi>Sunday.</hi> It continued fair the Wind at Weſt. At Sun Riſing I ſaw <hi>Shet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and the Iſles of <hi>Fair</hi> and <hi>Fowley</hi> alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; it being very clear ſo early. At ten I diſcerned <hi>Orkney;</hi> and at twelve at noon I took my departure from <hi>Fair Iſle,</hi> which then bore North from us, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant thirty Miles; being very fair wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>The 18th, <hi>Monday,</hi> The weather held as before, but the Wind was ſhifting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the W. and S. W. I made my way S. S. E. diſtance 82 Miles.</p>
            <p>The 19th, <hi>Tueſday.</hi> The day began with a freſh of Wind at W. N. W. and a little before noon we ſaw 3 Ships ſteering towards us. Whereupon, as not depending upon what the Governor of <hi>Wardhouſe</hi> his
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:50975:66"/> Secretary had told us, or giving entire cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of his news of a Peace with <hi>France,</hi> I cauſed a clear Ship to be made, and put our ſelves in as good a poſture of defence as we were able.</p>
            <p>I furled my ſmall Sails and Main-Sail, and by that time one of them came within ſhot of my weather Bow, I fired a ſhot for him to come Leeward of me; which he very honeſtly did, and confirmed the news of a Peace, to the great joy of our Hearts: for God knows we were but in a bad condition for managing our Guns in a way of fighting. This Ship was a <hi>Flemiſh</hi> Fly-boat bound to <hi>Greenland,</hi> for Whale-fiſhing. We preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after ſaw more Ships bound to the ſame place, and two Fiſher-boats alſo: But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now out of fear for Ships, we took no notice of the reſt. I made my way this 24 hours S. half Weſt diſtance 113 Miles.</p>
            <p>The 20th, <hi>Wedneſday.</hi> The Wind turned to the S. W. by W. ſo that I could not Seas in with our North Courſe, but was forced to ſtretch it away to the South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
            <pb n="110" facs="tcp:50975:67"/>
            <p>The 21ſt, <hi>Thurſday.</hi> The Wind re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to the N. N. E. and to the N. E. At 4 in the afternoon we had the ſight of <hi>Fulneſs</hi> to the S. and by E. off us. And no ſmall ſurprize was it to us, to ſee all the Land covered with Snow at this time of the year. A proſpect of ones own Country had been agreeable no doubt to any of us after ſo long an abſence by conſtraint and misfortune; but much more, had ſhe had the uſual garb of the ſeaſon. Soon after the wind came to the Eaſt, and obliged me to tack to the Norward in the night; we had much Snow and a freſh Gale, ſhifting N. E. and by N. and Eaſt North Eaſt.</p>
            <p>The 22d, <hi>Friday.</hi> In the Morning with a North N. E. wind, I came into <hi>Yarmouth</hi> Road, and thanks be to God, gave my Owners a ſight of their Ship: one of them, as I was told, but 3 hours before, having proffer'd his part for 3 Guineas, which was now worth 150 pounds.</p>
            <p>The Wind holding in the ſame point, and a fair Tide with me, I made no ſtop, but put through the Road, and ran
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:50975:67"/> that night into <hi>Alborough</hi> Bay; where the Wind coming Weſterly, brought me to an Anchor, ſo I Rid all night.</p>
            <p>The 23d, <hi>Saturday.</hi> By day-light per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving ſome Colliers coming out of the <hi>Neſſe,</hi> I hoiſted out my Long-Boat, and got ſome freſh proviſion among them; to our great Comfort. That afternoon I got out of <hi>Sled</hi> way; the Wind ſtill at Weſt.</p>
            <p>The 24th, <hi>Sunday.</hi> The Wind coming to the N. W. I got up to the Buoy off the Middle of <hi>Lee.</hi> It was calm and very warm, which brought our men into many Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, as pain in their Limbs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So that the next day I thought fit to ſend two of them up the River. I took notice of one of our Company, that went well to his Cabbin, but when we called him out to heave up the Anchor, he was ſo ſwoln, that we feared he would burſt. But then being got above <hi>Graveſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end,</hi> I hired a Wherry, and ſent him up with three more; ſupplying their places with ſome freſh and able men to bring up the Ship.</p>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:50975:68"/>
            <p>I and all the reſt, perceived our ſelves manifeſtly the worſe for the warm weather, as we called it; but 'tis well enough known almoſt to every one living, that ſuch a Temper of Air in <hi>England,</hi> both then, and for ſome time after, was ſcarce ever ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, when the year was ſo far advanced.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:50975:68"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
